哥 倫 比 亞 影 業    出 品
卡 帕 / 德 · 菲 娜    制 片
馬 丁 · 斯 科 塞 斯    作 品
領 銜 主 演 : 丹 尼 爾 · 戴 - 劉 易 斯
領 銜 主 演 : 米 歇 爾 · 菲 佛
領 銜 主 演 : 薇 諾 娜 · 瑞 德
片 名 : 純 真 年 代
又 譯 : 心 外 幽 情 ( 港 ) / 純 情 年 代
聯 合 主 演 :
傑 拉 丁 · 卓 別 林
邁 克 爾 · 高 夫
理 查 德 · E · 格 蘭 特
瑪 麗 · 貝 絲 · 赫 特
聯 合 主 演 :
羅 伯 特 · 肖 恩 · 萊 納 德
諾 曼 · 勞 埃 德
米 瑞 安 · 瑪 格 萊 斯
亞 歷 克 · 馬 克 溫
聯 合 主 演 :
僊 · 菲 利 普 斯
喬 納 森 · 普 雷 斯
亞 歷 克 西 斯 · 史 密 斯
斯 圖 爾 特 · 威 爾 遜
選 角 : 艾 倫 · 劉 易 斯
助 理 制 片 : 約 瑟 夫 · 瑞 迪
聯 合 制 片 : 布 魯 斯 · S · 普斯汀
片 頭 設 計 : 伊 蓮 & 索 爾 · 巴 斯
配 樂 : 埃 爾 默 · 伯 恩 斯 坦
服 裝 設 計 : 加 布 裏 埃 拉 · 佩 斯 庫 奇
剪 輯 : 塞 爾 瑪 · 斯 昆 梅 克
藝 術 指 導 : 丹 特 · 費 雷 蒂
攝 影 指 導 : 邁 克 爾 · 包 豪 斯
本 片 改 編 自 伊 迪 絲 · 沃 頓 所 著 同 名 小 說
編 劇 : 傑 伊 · 考 克 斯 & 馬 丁 · 斯 科 塞 斯
制 片 : 芭 芭 拉 · 德 · 菲 納
導 演 : 馬 丁 · 斯 科 塞 斯
紐約市  一八七零年代
哇
Well...
無法想像明戈特的家眷會穿這種衣服
I didn't think the Mingotts would have tried it on.
在劇院裏如此炫耀地
Parading her at the opera like that,
還讓她坐在梅·韋蘭德身旁
sitting her next to May Welland.
真奇怪
It's all very odd.
但她的經歷也挺奇怪
Well, she's had such an odd life.
他們會帶她參加博弗特家的舞會嗎
Will they even bring her to the Beauforts' ball, do you suppose?
如果那樣  一定會引起軒然大波
If they do, the talk will be of little else.
晚上好  韋蘭德太太  晚上好  梅
Good evening, Mrs. Welland. Good evening, May.
紐倫德  我的外甥女奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人
Newland. You know my niece Countess Olenska.
伯爵夫人
Countess.
希望你已經告訴過奧蘭斯卡夫人了
I hope you've told Madame Olenska.
告訴她什麼
What?
我們訂婚的事
That we're engaged.
我要全世界都知道
I want everybody to know.
我要在舞會中宣佈
Let me announce it this evening at the ball.
如果你能說服我媽的話
If you can persuade Mamma.
已決定的事何必提前
Why should we change what is already settled?
不過你可以告訴我表姐
But you can tell my cousin yourself.
她記得你
She remembers you.
我記得我們曾在一起玩
I remember we played together.
這一切勾起了我的回憶
How this brings it all back to me.
我記得大家兒時的模樣
I remember everybody here the same way,
穿著可笑的燈籠褲和長褲
in knickerbockers and pantalettes.
你是個討厭鬼  還在門後強吻過我
You were horrid. You kissed me once behind a door.
我喜歡的是你堂哥范迪  但他從不願瞧我一眼
But it was your cousin Vandie, the one who never looked at me, I was in love with.
你已經離開很久了
Yes, you have been away a very long time.
太久了
Centuries and centuries.
久得令我感覺自己已死  而這裏宛如天堂
So long, I'm sure I'm dead and buried, and this dear old place is heaven.
昔日的事情
It invariably happened,
每次都是千篇一律地發生
as everything happened in those days, in the same way.
一如往常  博弗特夫人在沒有丈夫的陪伴下
As usual, Mrs. Julius Beaufort appeared,
獨自前來
unaccompanied by her husband,
觀賞  珠寶之歌
just before The Jewel Song.
又照例在第三幕之後起身離去
And again, as usual, rose at the end of the third act and disappeared.
全城都知道這表示半小時後
New York then knew that a half hour later,
一年一度的博弗特歌劇舞會便要開始
the Beauforts' Annual Opera Ball would begin.
馬車早已恭候多時
Carriages waited at the kerb for the entire performance.
紐約人彼此都心照不宣
It was widely known in New York, but never acknowledged,
美國人急於離開娛樂
that Americans want to get away from amusement,
比到達還急切
even more quickly than they want to get to it.
紐約人家很少像博弗特家一樣
The Beauforts' house was one of the few in New York
有個舞廳
that possessed a ballroom.
這樣的房間  一年塵封三百六十四天
Such a room, shuttered in darkness 364 days of the year,
好似在
was felt to compensate
追悼博弗特家的任何壞事
for whatever was regrettable in the Beaufort past.
博弗特夫人瑞吉娜來自南卡世家
Regina Beaufort came from an old South Carolina family,
但其夫尤利斯  被認為是個英國後裔
but her husband Julius, who passed for an Englishman,
終日花天酒地
was known to have dissipated habits,
言談尖酸刻薄  而且身世不詳
a bitter tongue and mysterious antecedents.
攀附世族為他帶來社會地位
His marriage assured him a social position,
但卻未贏得尊敬
but not necessarily respect.
紐倫德·阿切爾並未像時下的年輕人一般
Newland Archer had not stopped at his club,
在俱樂部盤桓
as young men usually did,
他直接來到博弗特家豪宅參加舞會
but came directly to the Beauforts.
藉機宣佈婚訊
He wanted the announcement of his engagement
轉移眾人對伯爵夫人的閒言閒語
to divert gossip away from the Countess,
並表示對梅及其親族的支持
and show his most ardent support for May and her whole family.
博弗特家的豪宅規劃別出心裁
The Beaufort house had been boldly planned.
賓客無須擠進長廊
Instead of squeezing through a narrow passage
可由寬敞的客廳
to get to the ballroom, one marched solemnly
直趨宴會廳
down a vista of enfiladed drawing rooms.
晚上好
Good evening.
但穿過絳紅色的客廳時
But only by actually passing through the Crimson Drawing Room
你會看到  春神再臨
could one see The Return of Spring,
布格瑞這幅充滿爭議的裸體畫
the much-discussed nude by Bouguereau,
只有博弗特家敢公開展示
which Beaufort had had the audacity to hang in plain sight.
- 晚上好  - 晚上好  阿切爾先生
- Good evening. - Good evening, Mr. Archer.
阿切爾欣賞這種挑戰傳統的作風
Archer enjoyed such challenges to convention.
雖然他私下質疑墨守成規
He questioned conformity in private,
但在人前他卻不遺餘力的支持傳統
but in public he upheld family and tradition.
這個世界危危地保持平衡
This was a world balanced so precariously
只要一聲低語即可將它粉碎
that its harmony could be shattered by a whisper.
總之  身旁這班假道學之人
On the whole, Archer was amused
總令他覺得好玩
by the smooth hypocrisies of his peers.
甚至令他羨慕
He may even have envied them.
例如勞倫斯·萊弗茨
Lawrence Lefferts, for instance,
全紐約最講究儀表的人
was New York's foremost authority on form.
他那套細分各種鞋的規矩
And his opinion on pumps versus patent-leather oxfords
被奉為圭臬
had never been disputed.
他四處獵艷
On matters of surreptitious romance,
手腕令人嘆服
his skills went unquestioned.
西勒頓·傑克遜先生熟知各家譜系
Old Mr. Sillerton Jackson was as great an authority on family
其權威性可比勞倫斯·萊弗茨之精研儀表
as Lawrence Lefferts was on form.
奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人遠嫁歐洲的慘痛經驗
The mean and melancholy history of Countess Olenska's European marriage
他極欲一探究竟
was a buried treasure he hastened to excavate.
他就像個八卦活百科
He carried, like a calling card,
任何醜聞秘辛都一清二楚
an entire register of the scandals and mysteries
在表面太平的社交圈裏
that had smouldered under the unruffled surface
悶燒了五十年的陳年往事
of society for the last 50 years.
尤利斯·博弗特的成功秘訣  在於他的處世之道
Julius Beaufort's secret was the way he carried things off.
他可以若無其事地
He could arrive casually at his own party,
光臨自家舞會
as if he were another guest,
也可以大方地提早告辭
and might also leave early for a more modest,
溜進比較平民化的小公館
but comforting address in the East 30s.
他在事業上勇往直前
Beaufort was intrepid in his business,
在私生活上卻更加積極進取
but in his personal affairs absolutely audacious.
阿切爾的未婚妻對此  還有其他很多都一無所知
Archer's fiancee was innocent to all of these intrigues and of much else.
梅·韋蘭德代表上流社會最美的一切
May Welland represented for Archer all that was best in their world,
也是阿切爾所崇尚的  她使他不脫離這些規範
all that he honoured, and she anchored him to it.
我依你的意思告訴大家了
You see, I've told all my friends, just as you've asked.
我等不及了  我可真不願在舞會宣佈
Yes, I couldn't wait. Only I wish it hadn't had to be at a ball.
即使人多  這裏也只有我倆
But even here, we're alone together.
最糟的是我想吻你  但卻不能
The worst of it is that I want to kiss you, and I can't.
紐倫德
Newland.
你告訴艾倫了嗎
Did you tell Ellen as I asked you to?
我找不到機會說
No, I didn't have the chance after all.
她是我表姐  如果不先告訴她
She's my cousin, Newland. If others know before she does...
她離開久了  會很敏感的
It's just that she's been away for so long. She's rather sensitive.
我會說的  只是還沒見到她
Of course I'll tell her, dearest, but I didn't see her yet.
她臨時決定不來
She decided not to come at the last minute.
臨時決定
At the last minute?
她怕她的衣服不夠美
She was afraid her dress wasn't smart enough.
我們都說好看
We all thought it was so lovely,
但她執意回家
but she asked my aunt to take her home.
噢  原來如此
Oh, well.
很漂亮  很新潮
Very handsome. Very liberal.
想當年
In my time,
浮雕寶石鑲珠就算闊了
a cameo set in pearls was thought to be sufficient.
戴上的手才最能炫耀戒指
But it's the hand that sets off the ring, isn't it, my dear, Mr. Archer?
新式鑲法讓寶石更加耀眼奪目
It's the new setting. It shows the stone beautifully.
但老古板人會嫌樣式過於簡單
But it looks a little bare to old-fashioned eyes.
不是指我吧
I hope you don't mean mine, my dear.
我喜歡新東西
I like all the novelties.
我請巴黎名家做過手部雕塑
My hands were modelled in Paris by the great Roche.
他該幫梅做一個
He should do May's.
讓我瞧瞧  乖
Show me, child.
手都弄粗了
Her hand is so tempered.
那些時髦運動弄得關節粗大
It's these modern sports that spread the joints.
幸好皮膚依然白皙
But the skin is white.
婚禮何時舉行
And when's the wedding to be?
就快了  如果您肯支持我  明戈特夫人
As soon as ever it can, if only you'll back me up, Mrs. Mingott.
我們該讓小倆口好好認識彼此
We must give them time to get to know each other a little better, Mamma.
認識彼此
Know each other?
紐約世家子弟誰不認識誰
Everybody in New York has always known everybody.
有花堪折直須折
Don't wait till the bubble's off the wine.
四月完婚吧
Marry them before Lent.
說不定哪一天我會死於肺炎  而我要為他們辦喜宴
I may catch pneumonia any winter now, and I want to give the wedding breakfast.
你真疼孩子
What a kind offer.
就算曼森·明戈特夫人不是梅的奶奶
Even if she had not been grandmother to May,
小倆口訂婚後
Mrs. Manson Mingott would still have been the first
也一定會先拜見她
to receive the required betrothal visit.
她不僅是上流社會的大家長
She was not only the matriarch of this world,
簡直可以呼風喚雨
she was nearly its dowager empress.
紐約名流大多與她有親戚關係
Much of New York was already related to her,
其餘不是婚後家屬便是慕名之交
and she knew the remainder by marriage or by reputation.
當時建築慣用黃石砌牆
Though brownstone was the norm,
而她的豪宅外牆
she lived magisterially within a large house
卻大膽採用乳白色系石材
of controversial pale cream-coloured stone
座落於中央公園附近的密林中
in an inaccessible wilderness near the Central Park.
她老早就胖得
The burden of her flesh had long since made it impossible
爬不動樓梯
for her to go up and down stairs.
因此她又如常地大膽
So with characteristic independence,
搬到樓下生活
she had established herself on the ground floor of her house.
從會客室可以窺見她的臥房
From her sitting room, there was an unexpected vista of her bedroom.
那異國情調
Her visitors were startled and fascinated,
總令訪客驚嘆不已
by the foreignness of this arrangement,
總令人聯想起法國小說中
which recalled scenes in French fiction.
養著情夫的貴婦
This was how women with lovers lived in the wicked old societies.
其實她若願意
But if Mrs. Mingott had wanted a lover,
她大可養一個
the intrepid woman would have had him, too.
但她很滿足於現狀
For now she was content simply for life and passion
就讓別人把生活要聞報告給她
to flow northward to her door
她只期待紐倫德·阿切爾
and to anticipate eagerly the union of Newland Archer
早日迎娶孫女梅
with her granddaughter, May.
如此一來  紐約的兩大家族
In them, two of New York's best families
終能結為親家
would finally and momentously be joined.
- 再見  媽媽  - 再見
- Bye, Mamma. - Good-bye.
艾倫
Ellen!
- 女士們  阿切爾  -  泰莎姨母  梅
- Ladies. Archer. - Aunt Tessa, May.
博弗特  你是罕有的大方
Beaufort, this is a rare favour.
不需要這樣罕有
Unnecessarily rare, I'd say.
我遇見夫人
I met Countess Ellen in Madison Square,
她讓我陪她回家
and she was good enough to let me walk home with her.
有了她  這屋子將會歡樂許多
This house will be merrier now that she's here.
- 謝謝  - 搬凳子來  博弗特
- Thank you. - Beaufort, pull up that tuffet.
這個嗎
This one?
我要和你好好聊聊
I want a good gossip.
你知道我和梅訂婚了
Of course, you already know about May and me.
她老怪我沒告訴你
She scolded me for not telling you at the opera.
我早知道了  很開心
Of course I know, and I'm so glad.
這種喜事一定先得告訴親人嘛
One doesn't tell such news first in a crowd.
小心點
Careful there.
別把戒指纏進袖子裏
Don't let your ring catch on your sleeve.
- 再見  艾倫  - 再見  再見
- Good-bye, Ellen. - Good-bye. Good-bye.
再見
Good-bye.
有空來看我
Come and see me someday.
艾倫這麼粗心  公然和尤利斯一起
It's a mistake for Ellen to be seen parading up
走在最多人的第五大道
Fifth Avenue with Julius Beaufort,
而且就在她回國第一天
at the crowded hour, the very day after her arrival.
他生性風流
His behaviour is always so flagrant.
連他的太太都知道他有個情婦叫安妮·瑞茵
Even his wife must know about Annie Ring.
西勒頓·傑克遜喜歡頻頻光顧阿切爾的家
Sillerton Jackson enjoyed his frequent visits
而並不在乎那一頓晚餐
to the Archer home more than the actual dining.
紐倫德·阿切爾的母親和妹妹珍妮都怕生
Newland Archer's mother and his sister Janey were both shy women
不擅交際  卻又愛聽八卦
and shrank from society, but they like to be well-informed of its doings
所以全靠這位包打聽先生
and doted on their bachelor friend.
博弗特不懂細節
Certain nuances escape Beaufort.
當然啦  博弗特是個大老粗
Necessarily. Beaufort is a vulgar man.
但他有生意手腕
Nevertheless, no business nuances escape him.
很多人托他管理財產
Most of New York trusts him with its affairs.
我祖父常告誡我媽
My grandfather Newland always used to say to Mother,
千萬別讓博弗特認識我家的女孩子
"Don't let that fellow Beaufort be introduced to the girls."
至少他有認識君子的機會
At least he's had the advantage of association with gentlemen.
阿切爾家和明戈特家
The Archers and the Mingotts were two of the sturdiest branches
是紐約最顯赫的兩大家族
of New York's tangled family tree.
明戈特家喜愛梅的傳統嫻靜
Granny Mingott's family could embrace May's traditionalism
也能容忍艾倫的特立獨行
and tolerate Ellen's unconventionality.
但阿切爾家完全是老派作風
But Archer's family held fast to the old ways.
他的母親和妹妹凡事都得仰仗他
His mother and sister relied on him for every security.
他的母親對梅的母親說
He would always be, Mrs. Archer assured May's mother,
紐倫德是我們有力的臂膀
their "strong right hand."
我們新的親家表姐去參加舞會了嗎
And our new cousin, was she at the ball, too?
我欣賞明戈特家全為艾倫打氣  邀她一同觀賞歌劇
I appreciate the Mingotts wanting to support her, to have her at the opera.
也佩服他們家的向心力
I admire their esprit de corps.
但為何我兒子的喜訊
But why my son's engagement
要跟這女人的來去攪在一起
should be mixed up with this woman's comings and goings,
我真搞不懂
I don't see.
總之她沒去就是了
Well, in any case, she was not at the ball.
算她識趣
At least she had that decency.
先生
Sir?
噢  不
Oh, no.
下午她是戴闊邊帽還是軟帽
I wonder if she wears a round hat or a bonnet in the afternoon.
她看戲穿的那衣服好普通
The dress she wore to the opera was so plain and flat.
還是不去比較識趣
I'm sure it was in better taste not to go to the ball.
這與識趣無關  媽媽
It wasn't a question of taste, Mother.
梅說她嫌衣服不夠漂亮才沒去
May said the Countess decided her dress wasn't smart enough.
可憐的艾倫
Poor Ellen.
別忘了她從小的教養有問題
We must always remember the eccentric bringing-up she had.
一個會在成年舞會上
What can you expect of a girl
穿黑緞子的女人還有什麼指望
who was allowed to wear black satin at her coming out ball?
她嫁給伯爵後
It's odd she should've kept such an ugly name as Ellen
還是沒改掉艾倫這個俗氣的名字
when she married the Count.
換成是我  我就改成伊蓮
I should have changed it to Elaine.
為什麼
Why?
我也不知道
I don't know.
這樣聽起來
It sounds more
有波蘭味
Polish.
那反而會太特別
It certainly sounds more conspicuous,
她不會要的
and that can hardly be what she wishes.
如果她選擇特別  又有何不可
Why not? Why shouldn't she be conspicuous if she chooses?
她是嫁錯人  但用不著隱姓埋名
She made an awful marriage. But should she hide her head as if it's her fault?
難道她就該見不得人  好像讓自己丟了臉
Should she go slinking around as if she disgraced herself?
她遇人不淑就該遭人白眼
She's had an unhappy life. That doesn't make her an outcast.
我相信明戈特家的態度也跟他一樣
I'm sure that's the line the Mingotts mean to take.
別以為我非跟他們一樣不可
I don't have to wait for their cue if that's what you mean, sir.
聽說她在找房子
I'm told she's looking for a house.
準備長住
She intends to live here.
聽說她準備離婚
I hear she means to get a divorce.
希望如此
I hope she will.
這樁婚姻雖然使她飽受折磨
Understandably her marriage was intolerable.
但也有別的傳言
But there are the rumours, too.
我聽說了  伯爵的秘書
I've heard them. The secretary.
他協助她逃離夫家
He helped get her away from the husband.
聽說伯爵限制她的行動
They say the Count kept her practically a prisoner.
那伯爵的生活方式是很特別
Certainly the Count had his own way of life.
你認識他
You knew him?
我在法國尼斯聽過他的傳聞
I heard of him at Nice.
一表人才
Handsome, they say, but...
但睫毛過多
Eyes with a lot of lashes.
他不是玩女人  就是玩瓷器
When he wasn't with women, he was collecting china.
對這兩者都是一擲千金
Paying any price for both, I understand.
那麼為何要怪罪於她
Then where's the blame?
任何人都該像那秘書一樣
Anyone of us under the same circumstances would have helped the Countess,
幫助她
just as the secretary did.
一年後他仍幫著她
He was still helping her a year later then,
有人在瑞士洛桑看見他倆同居
because somebody met them living together at Lausanne.
同居
Living together?
有何不可  她有權過自己的生活
Well, why not? Who has the right to make her life over if she hasn't?
丈夫愛嫖  妻子就該守活寡嗎
Why should we bury a woman alive if her husband prefers to live with whores?
沒有人要她守寡啊
It's hardly a question of entombment.
她不是到這裏來了嗎
The Countess is here after all.
難道你贊成
Or do you believe
男女享有同等的自由嗎
a woman should share the same freedoms as men?
沒錯  我相信
I suppose I do. Yes, I do.
她的觀點顯然跟你一樣新潮
Well, apparently Count Olenski takes a similarly modern view.
我從未聽說伯爵試法使她回頭
I never heard of him lifting a finger to get his wife back.
三天後  發生了一件不可思議的事
Three days later, the unthinkable happened.
曼森·明戈特夫人發出請帖
Mrs. Manson Mingott sent out invitations
邀請大家前往餐敘
summoning everyone to a formal dinner.
如此隆重的晚宴絲毫馬虎不得
Such an occasion demanded the most careful consideration.
餐具全是上上之選
It required the appropriated plate.
桌旁須多添三名僕役
It called for three extra footmen,
每道菜都有兩盤外
two dishes for each course
還要檸檬甜酒
and a Roman punch in the middle.
請帖上寫著
The dinner, New York read on the invitation,
為歡迎奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人而設宴
was "to meet the Countess Olenska."
紐約名門全都婉謝
And New York declined.
遺憾  恕難奉陪
"Regret unable to accept."
連我們自家人也不願賞臉
And from some of our own family.
根本沒有人為她著想  就這樣給她難堪
No one cares enough even to conceal their feelings about the Countess.
真是情何以堪
This is a disgrace.
他們活在一個充滿寓意的世界裏
They all lived in a kind of hieroglyphic world.
從不具體表達真實的感受
The real thing was never said or done or even thought,
只是以約定俗成的寓意表示
but only represented by a set of arbitrary signs.
紐倫德懂得這些寓意
Archer knew these signs.
他們根本懶得掩飾
They were not subtle and were not meant to be.
這不僅是代表不理不睬
They were more than a simple snubbing.
根本就是對她封殺
They were an eradication.
有個地方  他可以去陳情
There was a single court of appeal.
他要請馮·德·萊登老爺子主持公道
He would plead their case before the van der Luydens.
你認為此事是有人在暗中搞鬼
And all this, you think, is due to some intentional interference by...
我敢肯定是拉瑞·萊弗茨
Larry Lefferts. Yes, sir, I'm certain of it.
馮·德·萊登夫婦德高望重
The van der Luydens dwelled above the city's families
地位崇高得近乎神聖
in a kind of super-terrestrial twilight.
老爺子處事自有公斷
Archer appealed to their exquisitely refined sense of tribal order.
紐倫德也直言無諱
And he spoke plainly.
每當萊弗茨太太
Whenever poor Gertrude Lefferts begins
懷疑先生出軌時
to suspect her husband of something,
他就收斂一陣子來轉移注意力
Larry starts making some great diversionary fuss to show how moral he is.
我最不喜歡這事的原則
Well, it's the principle that I dislike.
如果一家名門的子弟
I mean to say, if a member of a well-known family
獲得另一家名門的支持
is backed by that family,
整件事應該就不必爭議了
it should be considered final.
大家冷落伯爵夫人一事  我相信應該來問問你們
We all felt this slight on the Countess should not pass without our consulting you.
我們要為侄兒聖·奧斯特利公爵洗塵
So, we are giving a little dinner for our cousin, the Duke of St Austrey,
他搭的俄羅號  下周會到
who arrives next week on the Russia.
相信內人路易莎會和我一樣開心
I'm sure Louisa will be as glad as I am,
如果奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人前來參加晚宴
if Countess Olenska will let us include her among our guests.
當晚的場面極為隆重
The occasion was a solemn one,
但伯爵夫人姍姍來遲
but the Countess Olenska arrived rather late,
而她對自己的粗心仍毫不自覺
signalling a carelessness of which she was entirely unaware.
她大搖大擺  毫無愧容
She entered without haste or embarrassment.
走進坐滿了紐約達官貴人的客廳
The drawing room in which New York's most chosen company
可謂是冠蓋雲集
was somewhat awfully assembled.
奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人
Countess Olenska.
晚上好
Good evening.
- 歡迎光臨  - 晚上好
- We're delighted you're here. - Good evening.
聖·奧斯特利公爵  這是奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人
The Duke of St Austrey, may I present Countess Olenska.
他們動用了特瓦納·喬治二世時的餐具
The Trevenna George II plate was out.
還有來自東印度公司的馮·德·萊登·羅斯托夫細瓷
So was the van der Luyden Lowestoft from the East India Company.
以及達哥納王冠德比瓷器
And the Dagonet Crown Derby.
馮·德·萊登夫婦的這頓晚宴非同小可
Dining with the van der Luydens was at best no light matter.
能跟這位公爵親戚共進晚餐
Dining there with a duke who was their cousin
簡直猶如宗教儀式般隆重
was almost a religious solemnity.
馮·德·萊登家執行的教訓令人懾服
When the van der Luydens chose, they knew how to give a lesson.
失陪一下
Excuse me.
在紐約上流社會的社交場合中
It was not the custom in New York drawing rooms
女士起身離開一名男士
for a lady to get up and walk away from one gentleman
去跟另一名男士交談  於禮不合
in order to seek the company of another,
但伯爵夫人沒有守這規則
but the Countess did not observe this rule.
我想讓你跟我談談梅
I want you to talk to me about May.
你和公爵是舊識
You knew the Duke before?
在尼斯  每年冬天都會見到他
From Nice. We used to see him every winter.
他很喜歡賭博  常來我家玩大錢
He's very fond of gambling, and he used to come to our house a great deal.
他每晚都穿著同一件西服
He likes to wear the same suit every evening.
他認為它會帶來好運
He thinks it brings him luck.
我覺得他是世上最無趣的人
I think he's the dullest man I ever met.
但他在這兒卻被捧上天了
But he seems to be admired here.
知道我最心儀紐約的哪一點嗎
May I tell you what most interests me about New York?
不盲目遵循別人的傳統
Not all the blind obeying of tradition, somebody else's tradition.
把美國搞成外國的翻版就太可惜了
It seems stupid to have discovered America only to make it a copy of another country.
哥倫布會如此大費周章
Do you suppose Christopher Columbus would have taken all that trouble
只為和萊弗茨夫婦一同欣賞歌劇嗎
just to go to the opera with Larry Lefferts?
如果哥倫布知道拉瑞·萊弗茨在這兒
Well, I think if he'd suspected that Lefferts were here,
他就不會出航了
the Santa Maria might never have left port.
梅的看法也和你一樣嗎
And May, does she share these views?
就算一樣  她也不會說出口
If she does, she'd never say so.
你深愛著她嗎
Are you very much in love with her?
至死不渝
As much as a man can be.
這份愛可有極限
Do you think there's a limit?
就算有  我也還沒觸碰到
If there is, I haven't found it.
如此說來  這是真愛
It's really and truly a romance then,
而不是恭奉父母之命
not in the least arranged.
美國人的婚姻是不靠媒妁之言的
Have you forgotten? In our country we don't allow our marriages to be arranged.
對  我忘了  抱歉
Yes, I forgot. I'm sorry.
我總是犯這樣的錯誤
I sometimes make these mistakes.
我總忘了這裏樣樣都好
I don't always remember that everything here is good.
而那兒一無是處
That was bad where I came from.
抱歉
I'm so sorry.
不用
No.
這裏全都是你的朋友
But you know you are among friends here.
我知道  這就是我回來的原因
Yes, I know. That's why I came home.
晚上好  路易莎
Good evening, Louisa.
容我介紹梅·韋蘭德
May I present May Welland.
你一定想去陪梅
You'll want to be with May.
認識你十分榮幸
I'm so pleased to meet you.
她身旁已圍滿了我的情敵
She's already surrounded. I have so many rivals.
是啊
Yes.
那就再陪我多坐一會兒吧
Then stay with me a little longer.
好
Yes.
達哥納先生  容我介紹奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人
Mr. Urban Dagonet, may I present the Countess Olenska.
幸會
How do you do, my dear?
How do you do?
明天下午五點  我等你
Tomorrow then, after 5:00 I'll expect you.
明天見
Tomorrow.
失陪一下
Excuse me.
你人真好
It was good of you to devote yourself to Madame Olenska
肯這樣為奧蘭斯卡夫人出力
so unselfishly, dear Newland.
是我請亨利去救你的
I told Henry he really must rescue you.
我從未見過梅如此美麗
I think I've never seen May looking lovelier.
公爵認她是這裏最出色的女子
The Duke thinks her the handsomest woman in the room.
這是我的榮幸
It was my pleasure.
阿切爾先生
Mr. Archer.
你對寒舍有何感覺
So how do you like this odd little house?
我自以為猶如天堂
To me, it's like heaven.
- 你佈置得很雅致  - 是啊
- You've arranged it delightfully. - Yes.
我設法帶了些東西回來
Some of the things I managed to bring with me.
婚變後的殘骸
Little pieces of wreckage.
至少不像馮·德·萊登家那麼陰森
At least it's less gloomy than the van der Luydens',
在這裏獨處也不會太煎熬
and not so difficult to be alone.
儘管很多人認為馮·德·萊登家很陰森
I am sure it's often thought the van der Luydens' is gloomy,
但我倒是第一次親耳聽見
though I've never heard it said before.
你真的喜歡獨處嗎
But tell me, do you really like to be alone?
有朋友作伴就不覺的寂寞
As long as my friends keep me from being lonely.
你已經決定喜歡那兒
I see you've already chosen your corner.
是的
Yes.
- 請坐  - 謝謝
- Please, sit. - Thank you.
這是我最喜歡的時刻
This is the hour I like best.
你呢
Don't you?
我還以你早已將時間遺忘
I was afraid you'd forgotten the hour.
大概博弗特有時也很有趣吧
I am sure Beaufort can be very intriguing.
他帶我看了幾處房子  大家都勸我一定要搬
He took me to see some houses. I'm told I must move.
儘管這裏是高級住宅區
Even though this street seems perfectly respectable.
- 沒錯 但不夠時髦  - 時髦
- Yes, but it's not fashionable. - Fashionable?
時髦與否真的那麼重要嗎
Is fashion such a serious consideration?
對那些沒有更重要的事可操心的人而言
Among people who have nothing more serious to consider.
或許是我太獨立了吧
Perhaps I've been too independent.
我只求有人給我關愛和安全感
All I really want is to feel cared for and safe.
馮·德·萊登夫婦可說是全力出動了
Thank you. The van der Luydens do nothing by halves.
昨晚紐約名流都來捧你的場
All New York laid itself out for you last night.
他們人真好  我玩得很開心
It was so kind. Such a nice party.
奶油還是檸檬
Cream or lemon?
檸檬  謝謝
Lemon, please.
馮·德·萊登家族在社會上最有影響力
The van der Luydens are the most powerful influence in New York society.
他們因路易莎的健康不佳而絕少宴客
They very seldom receive because of Cousin Louisa's health.
或許就是這個理由吧
Perhaps that's the reason then.
謝謝  理由
Thank you. "The reason"?
愈神秘愈有影響力
For their influence. They make themselves so rare.
但你一定得告訴我
But, of course, you must tell me.
不  你來告訴我
No, it's you telling me.
- 謝謝  - 我們可以互相幫助
- Thank you. - Then we can both help each other.
可是我更需要幫忙
But I need help so much more.
已經有許多人告訴你該怎麼做了
There are so many people all ready to tell you what to do.
我獨居  恐怕會使許多人不以為然
I think they're all a little angry with me for setting up for myself.
至少你的家人會指點你
Still your family can advise you, show you the way.
紐約真的是個大迷宮嗎
Is New York such a labyrinth?
我以為條條道路都如第五大道一般寬敞筆直
I thought it was all straight up and down, like Fifth Avenue.
每條街都有編號
All the cross streets numbered,
每件東西都貼有大標籤
and big, honest labels on everything.
每件東西都有標籤  除了人以外
Everything is labelled, but everybody is not.
我需要你的提醒
Then I must count on you for warnings, too.
年長的女士都喜歡你  他們樂意伸出援手
All the older women like and admire you. They want to help.
我知道  只要她們沒聽見什麼傳聞
I know. I know, as long as they don't hear anything unpleasant.
難道這裏沒人肯聽實話
Does no one here want to know the truth, Mr. Archer?
真正的寂寞是住在這種好人之中
The real loneliness is living among all these kind people
他們要你戴上假面具
who only ask you to pretend.
不  千萬別這麼做
No, no, you mustn't.
奧蘭斯卡夫人
Madame Olenska.
艾倫
Ellen.
難道這裏的人也都不哭嗎
Does no one cry here either?
大概是沒有哭的必要吧
I suppose there's no need to.
阿切爾先生  晚上好
Mr. Archer, good evening.
今早沒見到你
We didn't see you this morning
我們不知是否要送花給韋蘭德小姐
and we weren't sure whether to send Miss Welland the usual...
以後每天一束百合
Lilies-of-the-valley. Yes, I think we better make that a standing order.
好的  先生
Very good, sir.
還有那些黃玫瑰  我給你另一個地址
And those yellow roses. I'll give you another address.
好的
Very good.
喬治
George!
奧蘭斯卡夫人  紐倫德·阿切爾先生
阿切爾先生  兩束花分送兩處
Mr. Archer, two separate orders.
馬上送出嗎
They'll go at once?
馬上  先生
At once, sir.
能聞著百合香醒來
It's wonderful to wake every morning
感覺真好
with lilies-of-the-valley in my room.
就像你在身旁
It's like being with you.
昨天花送遲了  我忘了時間
They came late yesterday, I know. Somehow the time got away from me.
但你總會記起來的
But still you always remember.
我也送了玫瑰給艾倫  可以嗎
I sent some roses to your Cousin Ellen, too. Was that right?
當然可以
Very right.
但今天午餐時她沒提起
She didn't mention it at lunch today though.
她說博弗特先生送給她漂亮的蘭花
She said she got some wonderful orchids from Mr. Beaufort,
亨利·馮·德萊登也送她一籃康乃馨
and a whole hamper of carnations from Cousin Henry van der Luyden.
她好開心
She was so very delighted.
難道歐洲人都不送花嗎
Don't people send flowers in Europe?
我知道你覺得訂婚期太長
I know you do consider it a long time.
沒錯
Very long.
可是奇弗斯夫婦訂婚一年半
But the Chiverses were engaged for a year and a half.
萊弗茨夫婦更長達兩年
Larry Lefferts and Gertrude were engaged for two.
媽媽希望我們能依照傳統
I'm sure Mamma expects something customary.
你從小就有主見
Ever since you were little, your parents let you have your way.
你也快二十二歲了  何妨跟你母親直說
You're almost 22. Just tell your mother what you want.
我不能拒絕她對我的最後要求
I couldn't refuse her the very last thing she'd ask of me as a little girl.
難道我們就不能任性一點嗎
Can't we just strike out for ourselves, May?
難道我們應該私奔
Shall we elope?
如果你願意  有何不可
Well, if you would, why not?
你是真心愛我  我好開心
You do love me, Newland. I'm so happy.
你可以更快樂的
Well, why not be happier?
無法更快樂了  親愛的
I couldn't be happier, dearest.
我拿戒指給艾倫看
Did I tell you I showed Ellen the ring?
她說沒見過比這更漂亮的
She thought it was the most beautiful setting she ever saw.
連巴黎的款式也比不上
She said there was nothing like it in the Rue de la Paix.
我好愛你  紐倫德
I do love you, Newland.
你做的每件事都好特別
Everything you do is so special.
這案子很棘手  我得借重你的長才
I want to call on your legal skills for a rather delicate matter.
奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人想離婚
Countess Olenska wants to sue her husband for divorce.
有人說她想再婚  儘管她矢口否認
It's been suggested she means to marry again, although she denies it.
請恕我因訂婚之故
Because of... I beg your pardon, sir, but because of my engagement,
你可否另請高明
perhaps one of the other members of the firm could consider this matter.
正因為你與她將有親屬關係
But precisely because of your prospective alliance,
她的家人也指明要你
and considering that several members of the family have already asked for you,
希望你能考慮接下
I'd like you to consider the case.
這是家務事  自家人出面協調比較妥當
It's a family matter. Perhaps it's best settled by the family.
他們的態度相當明確
Their position is clear.
他們堅決反對離婚
They're entirely and rightly against a divorce.
但奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人堅持要請教律師
But Countess Olenska still insists on a legal opinion.
但說真格的  何必要離婚
But really, what's the use of a divorce?
她在美國  他在英國
She's here. He's there.
中間隔著大西洋
The whole Atlantic's between them.
伯爵最近很慷慨
As things go, Olenski's acted generously.
他主動歸還一部分錢
He's already returned some of the money without being asked.
但也不會再多給了
She'll never get a dollar more than that.
當然啦  她並不在乎錢
Although I understand she attaches no importance to the money.
所以最好還是依她家人的意願
Considering all that, the wisest thing really, is to do as the family say.
就讓事情這樣子吧
Just let well enough alone.
我認為此事應由她決定
I think that's for her to decide.
你是否仔細想過
Have you considered the consequences
離婚會有什麼影響嗎
if the Countess decides for divorce?
對她的影響嗎
The consequences for the Countess?
對每個人的影響
For everyone.
伯爵對她只是做出大概的控訴
I don't think the Count's accusations amount to anything more than vague charges.
但總會惹來閒言閒語
It will make for some talk.
我聽說過伯爵夫人和那秘書
Well, I have heard talk about the Countess and the secretary.
沒看見文件前就聽說了
I heard it even before I read the legal papers.
這終究不是一件令人舒服的事
It's certain to be unpleasant.
不令人舒服
Unpleasant?
離婚總是令人不舒服吧
Divorce is always unpleasant. Don't you agree?
當然
Naturally.
那麼我就拜託你了
Then I can count on you?
她全家都拜託你了
The family can count on you.
你會勸她打消此意吧
You will use your influence against a divorce?
我先和她談談再說吧
I can't promise that, not until I've talked to the Countess.
我真搞不懂你
I don't understand you, Mr. Archer.
為何不讓你的親家
You want to marry into a family
免掉離婚官司呢
with a scandalous divorce suit hanging over it?
這跟我的婚約是兩回事
I don't think that has anything to do with the case.
可否派人將這個送給伯爵夫人
Can someone take this for me to the Countess, please?
重要
我必須見你
謝謝
Thank you.
敢不去你就死定了
You refuse such an invitation on threat of death.
真有這麼可怕
Is it so bad?
不然就等著大家慢慢折磨你吧
Not if you have a taste for slow agony.
我禁不起折磨的
That's something I've neglected to cultivate.
在馮·德·萊登家住三天
Three days at Skuytercliff with the van der Luydens.
帶著皮裘大衣和熱水瓶去吧
I think you better take your fur and a hot water bottle.
那房裏有那麼冷嗎
Is the house that cold?
不  但路易莎令人不寒而慄
No, but Louisa is.
阿切爾先生
Mr. Archer.
星期天到狄摩尼餐廳來吧
Join me at Delmonico's on Sunday instead.
我請你吃生蠔
I'm having a nice oyster supper in your honour.
包廂  風雅人士作陪
Private room, congenial company. Artists and so on.
真令人心動  我回來後還沒見過藝術家
That's very tempting. I haven't met a single artist since I've been here.
我可以介紹一些畫家給你認識
I know one or two painters I could bring to see you if you'd allow me.
畫家  紐約還有畫家嗎
Painters? Are there any painters in New York?
謝謝  但我想認識的是歌星
Thank you, but I was really thinking of singers,
演員  和音樂家等演藝人員
actors, musicians, dramatic artists.
我夫家常有許多音樂家來
There were always so many at my husband's house.
明天再告訴你決定吧
May I write tomorrow and let you know?
現在太晚了
It's too late to decide this evening.
- 現在叫晚嗎  - 是的
- Is this late? - Yes.
因為我還有要事和阿切爾先生談
Because I still have to talk business with Mr. Archer.
當然啦  紐倫德
Of course, Newland,
如果你能讓她改變心意
if you can persuade the Countess to change her mind about Sunday,
歡迎你來作陪
you can join us, too.
你認識畫家  經常來往嗎
You know painters then? You live in their milieu?
那倒沒有
Not exactly.
你喜歡畫作
But you care about such things?
當然  我在歐洲從不錯過畫展
Immensely. When I'm in Paris or London, I never miss an exhibition.
我很留意畫壇動態
I try to keep up.
以前我也熱愛繪畫
I used to care immensely, too.
我的生活總充滿了藝術氣息
My life was full of such things,
但我要忘掉過去  完全美國化
but now I want to cast off all my old life to become a complete American
就像其他人一樣
and try to be like everybody else.
你永遠都不會和其他人一樣
I don't think you'll ever quite be like everybody else.
別這麼說
Don't say that to me, please.
我想忘掉過去
I just want to put all the old things behind me.
我知道
I know.
萊特布賴爾先生告訴過我
Mr. Letterblair told me.
萊特布賴爾先生
Mr. Letterblair?
對  是他要我來的  我們在同一家事務所
Yes, I've come because he asked me to. I'm in the firm.
這麼說是你負責我的案子
You mean it'll be you who'll manage everything for me?
我可以和你談  那太好了
I can talk to you. That's so much easier.
對  我就是為此而來的
Yes, I'm here to talk about it.
所有文件我都看過了
I've read all the legal papers.
還有伯爵寄來的信件
And the letter from the Count.
寫得很惡毒
It was vile.
可是如果決定打官司
But if he chooses to fight the case,
他可能說一些  呃
he can say things that might be...
對你很不利的話
That might be disagreeable to you.
並鬧得滿城風雨
And say them publicly,
那些話是毀滅性的  即使
so that they could be damaging even if...
即使什麼
If?
即使毫無根據
Even if they were unfounded.
我在這兒  他怎麼中傷我
What harm could accusations like that do me here?
此地的流言殺傷力極強
Perhaps more harm than anywhere else.
儘管法律允許離婚  但民情不容
Our legislation favours divorce, but our social customs don't.
沒有例外嗎
Never?
尤其是如果女方
Well, not if the woman
起碼表面上  無論怎樣輕微也好
has appearances in the least degree against her,
以任何非傳統方法也好
has exposed herself by any unconventional behaviour,
有難堪的緋聞
to offensive insinuations and...
我的家人也是這麼說的
Yes, so my family tell me.
我們的家人  你將成為我的表妹夫
Our family. You'll be my cousin soon.
你也同意他們的說法
And you agree with them?
什麼事讓你冒險離婚
What could you possibly gain that would make up for the scandal?
自由
My freedom.
你不是已經自由了嗎
But aren't you free already?
職責所在  我得讓你知道
It's my business to help you see these things just the way
那些關愛你的人對離婚的看法
the people who are fondest of you see them, all your friends and relations.
如果我沒告訴你
If I didn't show you honestly how they judge such matters,
就是沒盡到責任
it wouldn't be fair of me, would it?
沒錯
No, it wouldn't be fair.
好吧
Very well. I'll...
我依你就是了
Do as you wish.
我
I...
我真的很想幫你
I do want to help you.
你的確幫了我
You do help me.
晚安  表妹夫
Good night, cousin.
求求你  別哭得那麼凄慘
For mercy's sake, don't cry so bitterly.
忘掉我所做的一切
Forget what I've done.
除非你答應我
On one condition.
不管是什麼條件我都答應
I accept it, whatever it may be.
別再說你愛我
Never speak a word of love to me again!
永遠不會
Never!
我發誓
On my honour.
上天保佑你
Heaven bless you.
永別了
Farewell.
精彩極了
It's fascinating.
每年這戲中一幕
Every season, the same play, the same scene,
總是令觀眾感動不已
the same effect on the audience.
很精彩吧  紐倫德
Remarkable, isn't it, Newland?
比我在倫敦看的還精彩
I'm enjoying it even more than the London production.
你出國還看呀
You see this play even when you travel?
- 我出國就是為了不想看這戲  - 那天是晚宴
- I travel to get away from it. - So was it a dinner?
斯特拉瑟斯太太作東
It was a reception at Mrs. Struthers'
雖訂在禮拜天
given on the Lord's Day but with champagne
但不僅有香檳和在桌上歌唱
and singing from the table tops.
聽說還有舞會
People say there was dancing.
這麼說是法國式的禮拜天
It was a real French Sunday then?
墮落的早期可真令人興奮
Well, dissipation can be wonderfully energising in the early stages...
你認為她的情人明天會送黃玫瑰嗎
Do you think her lover will send her a box of yellow roses tomorrow morning?
我
I...
我也在想這個問題
I was thinking about that, too.
告別的那一幕
The farewell scene.
我知道
Yes, I know.
我也深受感動
It touches me as well.
散場時我總是盡快離去  以免那一幕的情景揮之不去
I usually leave the theatre after that scene to take the picture away with me.
我收到梅從聖奧斯汀捎來的信
I had a letter from May from St Augustine.
他們總是南下避寒
They always spend the winter there,
因為她母親有支氣管炎
on account of her mother's bronchitis.
梅不在時你都做些什麼
And what do you do while May is away?
工作
I do my work.
我要告訴你  你的建議很對
I do want you to know what you advised me was right.
世事總令人飽受煎熬  我很感激你
Things can be so difficult sometimes, and I'm so grateful.
隔天  紐倫德·阿切爾為了尋找黃玫瑰
The next day Newland Archer searched the city in vain
走遍全紐約卻依然沒找到
for yellow roses.
他寫了一封信給奧蘭斯卡夫人
From his office, he sent a note to Madame Olenska
表示當天想去看她
asking to call that afternoon,
並要信差等她的答覆
and requesting reply by messenger.
但她卻毫無表示  次日亦然
There was no reply that day or the next.
當黃玫瑰再度出現時  紐倫德卻匆匆走過
And when yellow roses were again available, Archer passed them by.
第三天他才接到她的信
It was only on the third day that he heard from her by post,
是從馮·德·萊登的別墅寄出的
from the van der Luydens' country home.
紐倫德  那天在劇院看見你後  我便趕緊逃離
"Newland, I ran away the day after I saw you at the play,
好心的路登夫婦收留了我
"and these kind friends have taken me in.
我想靜靜地思考
"I wanted to be quiet and think things over.
這裏很安全  真希望你也在這裏
"I feel so safe here. I wish that you were with us.
謹此
"Yours sincerely."
萊弗茨邀他去哈德遜河度週末
He had received an invitation from the Lefferts for a weekend on the Hudson,
他連忙答應
and he hoped it was not too late to reply.
因為那兒離馮·德·萊登的別墅不遠
Their house was not far from the van der Luydens'.
我來瞭解你到底在逃避什麼
I came to see what you were running away from.
我知道你會來的
I knew you'd come.
那表示你想見我
That shows you wanted me to.
梅在信上說要我照顧你
Cousin May wrote. She asked you to take care of me.
- 其實不用她吩咐  - 為什麼
- I didn't need to be asked. - Why?
我就這麼孤苦無依嗎
Does that mean I'm so helpless and defenceless?
還是這兒的女人都太有福氣  什麼都不缺
Or that women here are so blessed, they never feel need?
缺什麼
What sort of need?
噢  拜託  別考我
Ohh. Please don't ask me.
我們說的不是同一門語言
I don't speak your language.
亨利把祖傳老宅借給我住  我帶你去看
Henry left the old Patroon house open for me. I want you to see it.
信中的你並不開心
When you wrote me, you were unhappy.
對  但有你在身旁就不同了
Yes, but I can't feel unhappy when you're here.
我不能久留
I shan't be here long.
我知道
I know.
如果你真的希望我來
Ellen, if you really wanted me to come,
如果真要我的幫助
if I'm really to help you,
你必須老實說你究竟在躲什麼
you must tell me what you're running from.
你是在躲避他嗎
Is he what you were running from?
還是在等他
Or what you expected?
我不知道他也來了
I didn't know he was here.
你好  博弗特  這邊請
Hello, Beaufort. This way.
奧蘭斯卡夫人正在等你
Madame Olenska was expecting you.
你好
Hello.
你讓我找得好苦
Well, you've certainly led me on a bit of a chase.
我大老遠來  只想告訴你  房子找到了
All this way just to tell you I'd found the perfect little house for you.
還沒公開出售  要買就得趁現在
It's not on the market yet, so you must take it at once.
阿切爾  你也來隱居嗎
Well, Archer, rusticating?
那一夜  他訂的書從倫敦寄來
That night he did not take the customary comfort
卻無法令他像往日一般開懷
in his monthly shipment of books from London.
單調的日子使他倍感無趣
The taste of the usual was like cinders in his mouth.
有時他甚至覺得
And there were moments when he felt
他快被往後的日子活埋
as if he were being buried alive under his future.
紐倫德  明天晚點來  我得向你解釋
"Newland, come late tomorrow. I must explain to you.
艾倫
"Ellen."
發生了什麼事嗎
Newland. Has anything happened?
對  我非見你不可
Yes. I found I had to see you.
- 怎麼啦  - 沒什麼
- What is it? - Nothing.
你每天做些什麼事
So tell me what you do all day?
有些人從費城和巴爾的摩而來
Well, there are a few very pleasant people
他們在旅館舉行野宴
from Philadelphia and Baltimore who are picnicking at the inn,
莫家弄了個草地網球場
and the Merrys are setting up a lawn tennis court,
可是沒有人會打
but nobody here's really heard of the game yet.
只有我和凱特帶了球拍
I have my racket, of course, and so does Kate Merry,
可她有嚴重的支氣管炎
but she's had this terrible case of bronchitis.
她還沒完全康復
She's still not quite got over it yet, so...
我來這裏
But I thought... I came here because I thought
就是希望你能避開那些社交
I could persuade you to break away from all that,
盡快跟我結婚
to advance our engagement.
你知道我有多麼想娶你嗎
Don't you understand how much I want to marry you?
我們何必再浪費一年呢
Why should we dream away another year?
我就是不明白
I'm not sure I do understand, Newland.
你對我是否變了心
Is it because you're not certain of feeling the same way about me?
你在胡說些什麼
What on earth do you mean?
是不是有第三者
Is there someone else?
第三者
Someone else?
你我之間
Between you and me?
我們把話談開來吧
Let's talk frankly, Newland.
我覺得你變了  特別是在我們訂婚之後
I've felt a difference in you, especially since our engagement.
什麼
Since our engagement?
如果沒有  談談也無妨
If it's untrue, then it won't hurt to talk about it.
如果有  我們更需要談談
And if it is true, then why shouldn't we talk about it now?
或許你找錯了對象
I mean, you might have made a mistake.
如果你不是我的理想對像
If I'd made some sort of a mistake, would I be down here,
我會催你盡快與我結婚嗎
asking you to hurry our marriage?
或許吧
I don't know. You might.
使自己沒有選擇的餘地
It would be one way to settle the question.
兩年前在新港
In Newport, two years ago,
我們訂婚之前
before we were promised,
大家都說你另有所愛
everyone said there was someone else for you.
我看過你們在舞會時
I even saw you with her once,
一起坐在陽台上
sitting together on a veranda at a dance.
她進門時神情落寞
When she came into the house, her face looked so sad.
我真為她難過  訂婚之後
I felt sorry for her, and even after, when we were engaged,
我仍忘不掉她的神情
I could still see how she looked and...
你就是在擔心這個
Is that... Is that all you've been concerned about?
那早就過去了
It's long passed.
那麼是其他事嗎
Then is there something else?
沒有  當然沒有
No. Of course not.
無論如何  紐倫德
Whatever it may have been, Newland,
我不能將快樂建築在別人的痛苦上
I can't have my happiness made out of a wrong to somebody else.
假如你對別人許下誓言
If promises were made, or if you feel in some way pledged to this person,
即使對方得因此而離婚
even if it means her getting a divorce,
也別為我而捨棄她
then, Newland, don't give her up because of me.
這根本就是子虛烏有
There are no pledges.
我沒對別人許下誓言
There are no promises that matter.
我一直想對你說
That's all I've been trying to say.
我們之間沒有第三者
There is no one between us. There is nothing between us, May.
所以我才催你
Which is precisely my argument for getting married.
盡快與我結婚
Quickly.
他覺得她又變回了純真的小女孩
He could feel her dropping back to inexpressive girlishness.
她總算釋懷了
Her conscience had been eased of its burden.
他心想  真美妙  如此的深情
It was wonderful, he thought, how such depths of feeling
卻和如此缺乏想像力共聚一身
could coexist with such an absence of imagination.
- 成功了嗎  - 沒有
- And did you succeed? - No.
還是希望您能幫我在四月完婚
No, I'd still like to be married in April, with your help.
你總算見識了明戈特家的厲害
Now you're seeing the Mingott way.
他們果真如此頑固不靈
Is this really so difficult?
這個家族一向如此
The entire family is difficult.
個個是老古板
Not one of them wants to be different.
不然就像艾倫的父母一樣
When they are different, they end up like Ellen's parents.
簡直是歐陸的遊牧民族
Nomads, continental wanderers.
帶著艾倫到處去
Dragging Ellen about,
為她花了大錢受教育  但總是斷斷續續
lavishing on her an expensive, but incoherent education.
在所有孫輩中
Out of all of them, I don't believe there's one
就屬艾倫最像我了
that takes after me but my little Ellen.
你很有眼光
You've got a quick eye.
為何沒娶她
Why in the world didn't you marry her?
她不在國內  我無緣娶她
Well, for one thing, she wasn't there to be married.
說得也是
No, to be sure.
現在還是娶不成  伯爵  你知道
And she's still not. The Count, you know.
寫信給萊特布賴爾先生
He's written to Mr. Letterblair.
要她回心轉意  條件隨她開
He wants her back, on her own terms.
伯爵倒沒為自己強辯
The Count doesn't defend himself, I will say that.
如果她執意不回去  那將會是她的損失
And Ellen will be losing a great deal if she stayed here.
那裏有她熟悉的生活
There's her old life,
尼斯的花園  珠寶  音樂和清談
gardens at Nice, jewels, of course, music and conversation.
她說她在歐洲默默無聞
She says she goes unnoticed in Europe,
但我知道  光是她的肖像畫就有九幅
but I know her portrait's been painted nine times.
此外  還有一個有心賠罪的丈夫
All this, and the remorse of a guilty husband.
我寧可她死
I'd rather see her dead.
真的嗎
Would you really?
你必須記得婚姻就是婚姻  艾倫已為人妻
We should remember marriage is marriage, and Ellen is still a wife.
艾倫  瞧瞧誰來了
Ellen! See who's here!
我知道
Yes, I know.
我去問你媽你去哪兒了
I went to see your mother to ask where you've gone.
你老是不給回信  我還擔心你病了
Since you never answered my note, I was afraid you might be ill.
因為他正忙著結婚
Well, he was in such a rush to get married, that's why.
他一下火車就往我這兒跑
Fresh off the train, and straight here.
求我為他說情  讓他早點把心上人娶進門
He wants me to use all my influence just to marry his sweetheart sooner.
這個嘛
Well, surely, Granny, between us,
我們都能勸說韋蘭德家照他的意思去辦
we can persuade the Wellands to do as he wishes.
紐倫德  聽見沒  一針見血  就像我一樣
There, Newland, you see? Right to the quick of the problem, like me.
我才跟他說他應該娶你的
I told him he should have married you.
他怎麼說
And what did he say?
噢  乖孫女啊
Oh, my darling,
自己去找答案吧
I leave you to find that out.
可惜我不能久留
I wish I didn't have to leave.
我會盡快來看你的
I shall see you very soon, I hope.
好
Fine.
我送你
I'll see you out.
何時可去找你
When can I see you?
斯特拉瑟斯家會在七點派車來接我
The Struthers are sending the carriage at 7:00.
晚上好
Good evening.
誰發神經送花給我
Who's ridiculous enough to send me a bouquet?
我沒要去舞會  也沒訂婚
I'm not going to a ball, and I'm not engaged.
納斯塔西婭
Nastasia!
尤利斯·博弗特先生  謹獻
就是有人這麼神經
Some people are always ridiculous.
把這些花送給街尾那戶人家
Take these to that nice family down the street.
嗯  她說的話有些真實
Well, I'll tell you, in almost everything she says,
也有虛假的成分
there's something true and something untrue.
為什麼
Why?
奶奶跟你說了些什麼
What has Granny been telling you?
她認為你會回到丈夫身旁
I think she believes you might go back to your husband.
她相信你至少會考慮一下
I think she believes you might at least consider it.
很多人相信我會做好些東西
A lot of things have been believed of me.
如果她相信我會考慮
But if she thinks I would consider it,
那表示她在代我考慮
that also means she would consider it for me,
也同時在考慮讓你提早結婚
as Granny is weighing your idea of advancing the marriage.
我和梅在佛州已經把話談開了
May and I had a frank talk in Florida.
那或許是我們的第一次
It's probably our first.
她想晚一點結婚  給我多一點時間
She wants a long engagement, to give me time.
多一點時間幹嘛
Time for what?
她認為我急著與她結婚
She thinks I want to marry her at once...
是為了逃避某人
To get away from someone that I care for
一個我用情更深的人
more.
讓你有時間為別的女人放棄她
Time to give her up for another woman?
如果我夠絕情的話
If I want to.
她簡直是個聖人
That's very noble.
沒錯
Yes.
真是荒謬至極
But it's ridiculous.
怎麼說
Why?
因為根本沒有第三者
Because there is no other woman?
是因為
No.
因為我非她莫娶
Because I don't mean to marry anyone else.
那個第三者也深愛著你嗎
This other woman, does she love you too?
根本沒有第三者  梅所懷疑的人根本就
There is no other woman! The person May was thinking of was never...
一定是接你的馬車來了
That must be your carriage.
對
Yes, I...
我該走了
I suppose I should be leaving soon.
到斯特拉瑟斯家去嗎
To Mrs. Struthers'?
對  人家邀我去  我就赴約  一個人太寂寞了
Yes. I must go where I'm invited, or I should be too lonely.
為何不同我一起去呢
Why not come with me?
其實梅猜得沒錯
May guessed the truth.
的確有第三者
There is another woman.
但不是她擔心的那一個
Only, not the one she thinks.
別對我調情  太多人對我調情
Don't make love to me, too many people have done that.
我是真心的
I've never made love to you.
如果可以
But you are the woman I would've married
我要娶你
if it had been possible for either of us.
是你讓它成為不可能的
You can say that when you're the one who's made it impossible?
- 我  - 你叫我別離婚
- I've made it? - Isn't it you who made me give up divorcing?
你在這屋裏勸我要犧牲
Didn't you talk to me here, in this house,
免得遭人議論
about sacrifice and sparing scandal?
為了成全你們  我乖乖聽你的話
And for May's sake, and for yours, I did what you asked me!
你丈夫在信裏說你
There were things in your husband's letter...
那封信唬不了我的
I had nothing to fear from that letter, absolutely nothing.
我只擔心你和梅  還有我的家人
I was just afraid of scandal for the family and you and May.
艾倫
Ellen.
沒有什麼
Nothing's...
沒有什麼是無法挽回的
Nothing's done that can't be undone.
我仍單身
I'm still free.
你也可以
You can be, too.
求你告訴我
Please, Ellen.
現在我還能娶梅嗎  你願意看見我娶她嗎
Lord, can I marry May now? Do you see me marrying May now?
你認為你可以問她這個嗎
I don't see you putting that question to May, do you?
事已至此
But I have to.
我別無選擇
It's too late to do anything else.
這不是真的
You say that because it's the easiest thing to say at this moment,
你只是在逃避
not because it's true.
我真搞不懂你
I don't understand you.
因為你不知道
You don't understand because you don't yet realise
你已改變了我
how you've changed things for me.
你對你所做的事渾然不知
You don't know all that you've done.
我做的事
All I've done?
你暗中為我做的事
All the good things you've done for me, Newland, that I never knew.
你去找馮·德·萊登  只因大家都不理我
Going to the van der Luydens' because people refused to meet me.
在舞會上宣佈婚訊
Announcing your engagement at the ball so there would be
如此一來多了一個家族支持我
two families standing behind me instead of one.
從前我並不知道別人是如此地鄙視我
I never understood how dreadful people thought I was.
直到外婆有一天不小心說溜了嘴
Granny blurted it out one day.
我好傻
I was stupid. I never thought...
我總以為到了紐約我就自由了
New York meant freedom to me.
每個人都那麼好  那麼樂於見到我
Everyone seemed so kind, and glad to see me.
他們怎會知道禁慾的痛苦
But they never knew what it meant to be tempted,
但你全都瞭解
but you did, you understood.
這些我從不知道
I'd never known that before.
而且比我所知的一切都還可貴
And it's better than anything I've known.
若你狠心  你也不會快樂
Newland, you couldn't be happy if it meant being cruel.
我怎能要你變心
If we act any other way,
我就是因你的人品而愛你
I'll be making you act against what I love in you most.
我再也無法任性而為
And I can't go back to that way of thinking.
難道你不懂嗎  除非放棄你  否則我無法愛你
Don't you see? I can't love you, unless I give you up.
艾倫  奶奶果然不同凡響
"Ellen, Granny's telegram was successful.
我媽媽已決定讓我們在四月結婚  只剩一個月了
"Grandma and Mamma agreed to marriage after Easter, only a month.
我會通知紐倫德  無法形容我內心的喜悅
"I will telegraph Newland. I'm too happy for words, and love you dearly.
感激你的梅
"Your grateful cousin, May."
導演客串出演攝影師一角
婚禮之前盛傳
There had been wild rumours right up to the wedding day
明戈特老夫人要親自觀禮
that Mrs. Mingott would actually attend the ceremony.
她甚至請木匠去量教堂的長椅
It was known that she had sent a carpenter to measure the front pew,
瞭解是否需要加大
in case it might be altered to accommodate her.
不過最後她還是作罷
But this idea, like the great lady herself, proved to be unwieldy,
只決定在上午宴請大家
and she settled for giving the wedding-breakfast.
奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人表示
The Countess Olenska sent her regrets.
將有遠行而無法出席
She was travelling with an aunt.
但她送了一匹蕾絲賀喜
But gave the bride and groom an exquisite piece of old lace.
兩位姨媽提供了蜜月小套房
Two elderly aunts in Rhinebeck offered a honeymoon cottage.
當時英國貴族也流行這樣
And, since it was thought very English to have a country house on loan,
小倆口欣然接受
their offer was accepted.
不過後來發現小屋不能住
When the house proved suddenly uninhabitable, however,
但亨利·馮·德萊登慷慨借出
Henry van der Luyden stepped in to offer an old cottage
他住家附近的別墅
on his property nearby.
梅接受了  好讓紐倫德驚喜
May accepted the offer as a surprise for her husband.
她沒見過這房子
She'd never seen the house,
只聽艾倫提起過
but her cousin, Ellen, had mentioned it once.
她說全美國只有這裏
She had said it was the only house in America
讓她覺得幸福可期
where she could imagine being perfectly happy.
他們到了上流社會蜜月必經之地  梅從未去過
They travelled to the expected places, which May had never seen.
紐倫德在倫敦訂做新衣
In London, Archer ordered his clothes.
兩人同游國家畫廊  一起欣賞歌劇
And they went to the National Gallery, and sometimes to the theatre.
希望這套衣服不會太俗氣
I hope I don't look ridiculous.
我沒在倫敦參加過晚宴
I've never dined out in London.
英國婦女的晚禮服和其他人一樣
English women dress just like everybody else in the evening, don't they?
可是她們在劇院裏
How can you say that when they're always at the theatre
都穿著舊禮服
in old ball dresses and bare heads?
或許把新衣留在家裏穿吧
Well, maybe they save their new dresses for home.
這麼說我不該穿這一件
Then I shouldn't have worn this.
你這樣很好看
No, you look very fine.
真的很好看
Really quite beautiful.
她在巴黎添購了許多新衣
In Paris, she ordered her clothes.
出自御用裁縫之手  買了幾大箱
There were trunks of dresses from Worth.
他們還逛了圖勒花園
They visited the Tuileries.
梅的雙手也被製成了大理石雕像
May's hands were modelled in marble at Roche's studio.
他們偶爾應邀作客
And occasionally, they dined out.
莫泊桑真的教你寫作嗎
But tell me. You were saying that you were actually advised here by Maupassant?
對  不幸的是他勸我就此封筆
Yes. Unfortunately, I was advised not to write.
阿切爾沉浸在新婚的喜悅中
Archer embraced his new marriage,
甚至恢復了對婚姻的看法
even as he reverted to his old inherited ideas about matrimony.
畢竟依照傳統總是比較省事
It was less trouble to conform with tradition.
解放給梅也是徒然
There was no use trying to emancipate a wife
她絲毫不覺得自己受到束縛
who hadn't the dimmest notion that she was not free.
我們在倫敦時
When we were in London,
只在國家畫廊待了一天
we could only manage one day at the National.
我們還去了卡太太和哈太太家
We were taken up by a Mrs. Carfry and Mrs. Harle...
我們相談甚歡  他很有意思
We had an awfully good talk. He's an interesting fellow.
我們聊了書本等等的事
We talked about books, and many different things.
我想邀他共進晚餐
I thought I'd invite him to dinner.
- 那個法國人  - 對
- The Frenchman? - Yes.
我和他談話的機會不多
I didn't have much chance to talk to him,
他不是很粗俗嗎
but wasn't he a little common?
粗俗
Common?
我認為他很聰明
I thought he was clever.
我倒沒發現到這一點
I suppose I shouldn't have known if he was clever.
我不邀他就是了
Then, I won't ask him to dine.
他突然感到一陣涼意
With a chill, he knew that in future,
以後有很多問題  將會如此為他先行解決
many problems would be solved for him in this same way.
人們說新婚後半年最難相處
The first six months of marriage were usually said to be the hardest.
之後
And after that, he thought they would have
雙方的棱角都被磨平了
pretty nearly finished polishing down all the rough edges.
但梅施的壓力  把他最想保持的棱角
But May's pressure was already wearing down
都快要磨平了
the very roughness he most wanted to keep.
對於奧蘭斯卡夫人的渴望
As for the madness with Madame Olenska,
他強迫自己
Archer trained himself to remember it
將它當成婚前最後一次考驗
as the last of his discarded experiments.
她是他記憶之中最令他悲傷
She remained in his memory simply as the most plaintive,
哀痛的  一絲幽魂
and poignant of a line of ghosts.
新港射箭俱樂部  八月
她真是厲害
She's very deft.
她在其他場合才不懂一矢中的
Yes, well, that's the only kind of target she'll ever hit.
沒人會嫉妒梅的勝利
No one could ever be jealous of May's triumphs.
她好像不論輸贏
She managed to give the feeling that she would have been
也永遠如此嫻靜
just as serene without them.
但在她那平和甜美的簾幕之後
But what if all her calm, her niceness,
是否
were just a negation,
只是一片空白呢
a curtain dropped in front of an emptiness?
紐倫德感覺自己從未將簾幕掀起
Archer felt he had never yet lifted that curtain.
好漂亮
Quite stunning, isn't it?
這獎品是博弗特提供的嗎
It's Julius Beaufort who donates the club's prizes, isn't it?
標準的博弗特作風
This looks like him, of course.
留著當傳家之寶吧
It will make quite an heirloom, my dear.
將來送給你的長女吧
You should leave it to your eldest daughter.
怎麼了  難道你不生女兒  只生兒子
What's the matter? Aren't there going to be any daughters? Only sons?
我說錯了嗎
What, can't I say that either?
瞧她害臊的
Look at her blushing.
艾倫  艾倫  你在樓上嗎
Ellen! Ellen, are you upstairs?
她剛從樸茨茅斯來
She's over from Portsmouth, spending the day with me.
真討厭  她不想住在這裏
It's such a nuisance. She just won't stay in Newport.
非要呆在那破地方  叫什麼來著  布朗克斯
Insists on putting up with those... What's their names? Blenkers.
我老早就懶得跟年輕人辯了
But I gave up arguing with young people 50 years ago. Ellen!
抱歉  夫人
I'm sorry, ma'am.
艾倫小姐出去了
Miss Ellen's not in the house.
她走了
She's left?
我看見她去海邊了
I saw her going down the shore path.
乖  去把她找回來
Run down and fetch her like a good grandson.
我要跟梅聊聊博弗特的八卦
May and I will have a gossip about Julius Beaufort.
快去  她也想見見你們
Go ahead. I know she'll want to see you both.
博弗特真的給了情婦安妮·瑞茵鑽石手鐲嗎
Is it true Beaufort has given Annie Ring a diamond bracelet?
聽說他打算要帶她來
I hear he even plans to bring her to Newport.
暌違一年半
He had heard her name often enough
他還是經常聽見她的名字
during the year and a half since they had last met.
他對她的動態時有所聞
He was even familiar with the main incidents of her life.
但這並未激起任何漣漪
But he heard all these accounts with detachment,
只像是聽見一個死人的陳年往事
as if listening to reminiscences of someone long-dead.
但過去卻突然鮮活起來
But the past had come again into the present,
好像是最近出土的原始洞穴
as in those newly-discovered caverns in Tuscany,
孩子們帶著火把闖入
where children had lit bunches of straw,
卻看見早已作古之人  在牆上盯著你看
and seen old images staring from the wall.
他決定給自己一個機會
He gave himself a single chance.
帆船駛過燈塔前  她若轉身
She must turn before the sailboat crosses the lime rock light.
他就走向她
Then, he would go to her.
真遺憾你沒找到她  聽說她變了
I'm sorry you didn't find her, but I've heard she's so changed.
變了
Changed?
都不理會老朋友了
So indifferent to her old friends,
還獨自去樸茨茅斯避暑  她搬到華盛頓
summering in Portsmouth, moving to Washington.
或許是嫌我們乏味無趣
Sometimes, I think we've always bored her.
或許回到丈夫身旁會使她快活些
I wonder if she wouldn't be happier with her husband after all.
我從不知道你如此殘忍
I don't think I've ever heard you be cruel before.
殘忍
Cruel?
即使是魔鬼也不會覺得人在地獄會快樂
Even demons don't think people are happier in Hell.
當初她就不該遠嫁海外
Then she shouldn't have married abroad.
讓我來  走  駕
Here, let me. Go on. Walk on.
布朗克斯母女  邀布朗克斯母女吃飯
The Blenkers? A party for the Blenkers?
誰啊
Who are they?
她們住樸茨茅斯  艾倫住在她們家避暑
The Portsmouth people, I think. The ones Countess Olenska is staying with.
西勒頓夫婦敬邀週三下午三點
"Professor and Mrs. Emerson Sillerton request the pleasure Wednesday afternoon,
歡迎布朗克母女們蒞臨
"At 3:00 o'clock, punctually to meet Mrs. and the Misses Blenker.
紅色院牆  凱瑟琳街
"Red gables, Catherine Street."
我們不好意思不去
I don't think we can decline.
何必去呢  他是個考古學家
I don't see why, really. He's an archaeologist.
他可是西勒頓·傑克遜的表兄
And he's Sillerton Jackson's cousin.
好吧
Of course.
一定要有人去才行
Some of us will have to go.
我去  珍妮  陪我去吧
I'll go over. And, Janey, why don't you come with me?
艾倫一定會去的  你可以見到她的
I'm sure Cousin Ellen will be there. It will give you a chance to see her.
紐倫德  你一個人可以打發時間吧
Newland, you can find a way to spend your afternoon, can't you?
我想我會好好利用時間
I think for a change, I'll just save it instead of spending it.
也許我會開車去農場  看看布魯厄姆的新馬
Maybe I'll drive to the farm to see about a new horse for the brougham.
至少傑克遜家沒有選擇杯賽日來舉辦他們的宴會
Well, at least the Jacksons didn't choose the day of the Cup Race for their party.
當然啦  如果真是那樣我也不感到奇怪
Of course, I shouldn't be surprised if they had.
你好
Hello?
抱歉  是你按鈴嗎  我正在吊床上睡覺
I'm sorry. Did you ring? I've been asleep in the hammock.
把你吵醒了  抱歉
Well, I didn't mean to disturb you.
布朗克小姐嗎  我叫紐倫德·阿切爾
Are you Miss Blenker? I'm Newland Archer.
久仰大名
Yes. I've heard so much about you.
我想來這兒買匹新馬
I came to the island to look for a new horse.
本想登門拜訪  但沒人在家
I thought I'd call, but the house seems to be empty.
對  大夥兒都去赴宴去了
It is empty. They're all at the party.
只有發燒的我和奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人沒去
Everyone's there, but me with my fever, and Countess Olenska.
噢  你找到我的傘了
Oh, you found my parasol.
這是我最愛的一把傘  喀麥隆制的
It's my best one. It's from the Cameroons.
真漂亮
Well, it's very pretty.
伯爵夫人不在嗎
The Countess was called away?
對  她接到來自波士頓的電報
Yes. A telegram came from Boston.
她說她得去兩天
She said she might be gone for two days.
我好喜歡她的髮型  你呢
I do love the way she does her hair, don't you?
好像是小說中的女主角
It reminds me of Sir Walter Scott.
你不知道  我明天也要去波士頓一趟
You don't know... I'm sorry, but I have to be in Boston tomorrow.
你知道她住在哪兒嗎
You wouldn't happen to know where she was staying?
艾倫
Ellen.
我是來出差的  剛到
I'm here on business. I just got here, actually.
你的髮型變了
You're doing your hair differently.
女傭沒來
Only because my maid's not with me.
她留在樸茨茅斯了  我只來兩天  所以沒帶她來
She stayed back in Portsmouth. I'm here only for two days. It didn't seem worthwhile.
你一個人來的
You are travelling alone?
對
Yes.
你認為太危險嗎
Why? Do you think it's a little dangerous?
只是不太符合傳統
Well, it's unconventional.
大概是吧
Yes, I suppose it is.
我剛做了更有違傳統的事
I've just done something so much more unconventional.
我拒絕拿回屬於自己的錢
I refused to take back money that belonged to me.
有人找你談了嗎
Someone came with an offer?
什麼條件
What were the conditions?
我回絕了
I refused.
- 告訴我是什麼條件  - 也沒什麼
- Tell me the conditions. - Nothing unbearable, really.
只是偶爾扮演女主人
Just to sit at the head of his table now and then.
他不計代價要你回去嗎
And he wants you back at any price?
很高的代價
Well, it's a considerable price.
至少對我而言
At least, it's considerable for me.
你是來見他的嗎
So, you came to see him?
在這兒見我丈夫  怎麼可能
My husband? Here? No, of course not.
他托人來傳話
No. He sent someone.
他的秘書
His secretary?
對
Yes.
他還沒離開
He's still here, in fact.
他堅持留下  等待我改變心意
He insisted on waiting, in case I changed my mind.
紐倫德  你一點都沒變
You haven't changed, Newland.
我變了  見到你後才又變回樣
I had changed until I saw you again.
求求你別再說了
Please don't.
讓我陪你一天吧  我不會說任何煩心的話
Just give me the day. I'll say anything you like, or nothing.
你允許我才開口說話
I won't speak unless you tell me to.
我只想陪陪你
All I want is some time with you.
他會去旅館找你嗎
I want to get you away from that man. Is he coming to hotel?
- 十一點會來  - 我們該走了
- At 11:00... - Well, let's go now.
我得留個紙條
I'll have to leave a note at the hotel.
寫在這上面吧  我有紙
Write on this. I have the paper.
瞧  這都是命運的安排
You see how everything is predestined?
看見沒  這是新式自來水筆
And these? Have you seen these? The new stylographic pen.
就像
It's just like...
就像甩溫度計裏的水銀
It's like jerking down the mercury in a thermometer. Now.
試試看
Try that.
沒法寫
It's not working.
應該沒問題了
That should do it.
- 要我拿進去嗎  - 等我一下
- Shall I take it in? - I'll be only a moment.
那天你怎麼沒去海邊找我
Why didn't you come down to the beach to get me the day I was at Granny's?
因為你沒回頭
Because you didn't turn around. I swore...
我發誓你回頭我才叫你
I swore I wouldn't call you unless you turned around.
我是故意不轉身的
But I didn't look around on purpose.
你知道
You knew?
你看見你的馬車
I recognised the carriage when you drove in.
所以我才去海邊
So, I went to the beach.
躲我躲得遠遠的
To get as far away from me as you could.
對  盡我所能
As I could, yes.
我們還是得面對現實
Well, you see, it's no use. It's better if we face each other.
我只想對你坦白
I only want to be honest with you.
所以你欣賞博弗特
Honest? Isn't that why you always admired Julius Beaufort?
他比我們任何人都坦白
He was more honest than the rest of us, wasn't he? We've no character.
我們全是假道學
No colour, no variety.
你為何不回歐洲
I don't know why you don't just go back to Europe.
- 我想是為了你吧  - 我
- I believe that's because of you. - Me?
我聽了一個女人的話  娶了另一個女人
I'm the man who married one woman because another one told him to.
你答應過今天不談這些事的
You promised not to say such things today.
我沒有辦法不提
I can't keep that promise.
梅呢  梅的感受呢
What about May? What about how May feels?
如果你把我的婚姻當成是某種勝利
If you're using my marriage as some victory of ours,
你就沒有不回去的理由
then there's really no reason on earth why you shouldn't go back.
你讓我首度見識到現實
You gave me my first glimpse of a real life.
又要我虛偽度日
And then you told me to carry on with a false one.
沒有人能承受這種苦
No one can endure that.
我正在承受
I'm enduring it.
我知道你會回去的
What's the use? I know you'll go back.
我不會的
I won't. Not yet.
只要你我還熬得下去  我不會的
Not as long as we both can stand it.
你不該過這種日子
This is not a life for you.
我心甘情願  只要它是你生活的一部分
It is, as long as it's part of yours.
你不會回去吧
You won't go back?
我不會回去
I won't go back.
他將再次遇見她
He would see her again.
在劇院或在宴會上
At the theatre, or a reception.
或許就坐在她身旁
Perhaps he might be seated next to her.
或許他們還有獨處的機會
Perhaps they might have another time alone, somewhere.
但他不能沒有她的日子
But he could not live without seeing her.
♪ Marble Halls ♪ Single by Enya
♫ 而我亦懷夢  最讓我著迷的是 ♫
♫ But I also dreamt which charmed me most ♫
♫ 你愛我依然 ♫
♫ That you loved me still the same ♫
♫ 你愛著我 ♫
♫ That you loved me ♫
♫ 你愛我依然 ♫
♫ You loved me still the same ♫
♫ 你愛著我 ♫
♫ That you loved me ♫
♫ 你愛我依然 ♫
♫ You loved me still the same ♫
您就是阿切爾先生
Mr. Archer, I think.
正是
Yes.
我姓裏維埃
My name is Riviere.
去年我們在巴黎曾一起吃飯
I dined with you in Paris last year.
對  抱歉  我一時沒想起來
Yes. I'm sorry. I didn't quite recall.
我昨天在波士頓看見你  所以一眼就認出你來
Quite all right. I had the advantage. I saw you in Boston yesterday.
我奉奧蘭斯卡伯爵之命前來
I came here on Count Olenski's behalf.
我相信她該回到丈夫身邊
Because I believed in all good faith that she should return to him.
抱歉
Forgive me.
抱歉  先生
Forgive me, monsieur,
我真的不明白
but I really don't understand your purpose
你為何來找我
in coming to see me.
她變了
She's changed, monsieur.
您跟她是舊識嗎
You knew her before?
我常在伯爵家中見到她
I used to see her at her husband's house, yes.
伯爵不會將此事托給陌生人
Well, the count would not have entrusted my mission to a stranger.
你提到她變了
This change that you mentioned.
這是我頭一遭見到她真情流露
It may only have been my seeing her for the first time,
美國式的真情流露
as she is, as an American.
她本有心做個賢妻良母
She made her marriage in good faith.
但伯爵卻無法體會
It was a faith the Count could not share,
難以理解
could not understand.
所以  她的信念
So, her faith was...
粉碎了
Detruit?
- 破裂了  毀滅了  - 毀滅了
- Broken. Destroyed. - Destroyed.
她回歐洲雖可過優裕的生活
Returning to Europe would mean a life of some comfort,
但犧牲太大
and considerable sacrifice.
而且難以再續前緣
And, I would think, no hope.
當然了  我會依約
I will, of course, fulfil my obligation to the Count,
拜訪她的家人
and meet with the family.
並轉達伯爵的意願
I will tell them everything that he suggests, and wishes for the Countess.
但也希望你能動用你的影響力
But I would ask you to use your influence with them.
求你叫她千萬別回頭
I beg you, monsieur. Do not let her go back.
巴克斯特·潘尼羅夫人死後
When old Mrs. Baxter Pennilow died,
家人才發現
they found her standing order,
她有四十八套大師做的女裝  仍原封不動
48 Worth dresses, still wrapped in tissue paper.
她的女兒守完孝之後
When her daughters left off their mourning,
竟穿那些衣服去聽音樂會
they wore the first lot to the symphony
毫不在意流行的趨勢
without looking in advance of the fashion.
他曾在華盛頓寫信給她
He had written to her once in Washington,
只是問她何時能再見面
just a few lines asking when they would meet again.
她回答  時機未到
And she wrote back, "Not yet."
儘管風格已經改變
And even that had the front panel changed.
博弗特帶動了新流行
No, I think it was Julius Beaufort who started the new fashion.
回國時他讓太太穿新衣亮相
By making his wife clap her new clothes on her back as soon as they arrived.
幸好她身世顯赫  否則就像
I must say, it takes all Regina's distinction not to look like...
他在外面養的女人
Her rivals?
他的情婦安妮·瑞茵
Like that Annie Ring.
留點口德
Careful, dear.
這已經是公開的秘密
Everybody knows.
的確
Indeed.
他總是亂投資
Beaufort always put his business around.
現在生意垮了  他必須給大家一個交代
And now that his business is gone, there are bound to be disclosures.
垮了  有那麼糟嗎
Gone? Is it really that bad?
簡直是一塌糊塗
As bad as anything I ever heard of.
每個我們認識的人都會受到影響
Most everybody we know will be hit one way or another.
他太太當然是最大的受害者
Very difficult for Regina, of course. And, it's a pity.
奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人回絕伯爵也是不智之舉
It's certainly a pity that Countess Olenska refused her husband's offer.
何以見得
Why, for God's sake?
以最基本的角度來看
Well, to put it on the lowest ground,
- 她現在靠什麼生活  - 生活
- what's she going to live on now? - Live on?
如今博弗特
I mean, now that Beaufort...
你這是什麼意思
What the hell does that mean, sir?
她大部分的錢都交由博弗特投資
Most of her money's invested with Beaufort.
而且她娘家也不再資助她
And the allowance she's been getting from the family is so cut back.
她應該還有錢
I'm sure she has something.
一點錢
I would think a little.
還債之後也所剩無多了
Whatever remains after sustaining more debt.
她娘家很在意裏維埃的話
I know the family paid close attention to Monsieur Riviere,
而且非常審慎地評估了伯爵的條件
and considered the Count's offer very carefully.
如果大家都希望她成為博弗特的情婦
If everyone had rather she be Beaufort's mistress
那麼你做得一點都沒錯
than some decent fellow's wife, you've all gone about it perfectly.
她是不會回去的
She won't go back.
那只是你個人的想法
That's your opinion, eh?
沒錯
Well, no doubt you know.
我想她大可求明戈特夫人
I suppose she might still soften Catherine Mingott,
給她一些生活費
who could give her any allowance she chooses,
但其他家人都希望她回歐洲
but the rest of the family have no particular interest in keeping her here.
他們會由她
They'll simply let her...
自生自滅
Find her own level.
晚上好  先生
Evening, sir.
謝謝  馬丁
Thank you, Martin.
這盞燈又在冒煙  找傭人來修
That lamp is smoking again. The servant should see to it.
對不起
I'm sorry.
我得去華盛頓幾天
I may have to go to Washington for a few days.
什麼時候
When?
明天  抱歉  我早該訴你的
Tomorrow. I'm sorry. I should have said it before.
出差
On business?
有一件專利案
On business, of course. There's a patent case
在最高法院開庭
coming up before the Supreme Court.
萊特布賴爾剛把此案交給我
I just got the papers from Letterblair.
看來他是有意
It seems that he intended...
算了  太複雜了
Never mind. It sounds too complicated.
這盞燈就夠我煩的了
I have enough trouble managing this lamp.
讓我試試
Let me try that.
去別處走走也好
But the change will do you good.
你一定要去看看艾倫
And you must be sure to go and see Ellen.
抱歉打擾  夫人  你的信
Excuse me, ma'am, but this came for you while you were out.
你能拿去修一下嗎  愛麗絲
Do something about this, will you, Alice?
遵命  先生
Certainly, sir.
奶奶中風了
Granny's had a stroke.
中風
A stroke?
豈有此理
Ridiculous.
不過是感恩節多吃了點罷了
I told them all, it was just an excessive Thanksgiving.
那個醫生不僅小題大作  還唯恐天下不知
Dr Bencomb acted most concerned and insisted on notifying everyone.
好像要大家來聽我的遺囑
As if it were the last reading of my will and testament.
你們真乖  會來關心我
You're very dear to come.
但或許只是來分遺產的
But perhaps you only wanted to see what I'd left you.
奶奶  你真是胡言亂語
Granny, that's shocking!
是胡言亂語令我中風的
It was shock that did this to me.
不  謝了  這都要怪瑞吉娜·博弗特太太
No. Thank you. It's all due to Regina Beaufort.
她昨晚來找我  求我
She came here last night, and she asked me...
求我  虧她說得出口
She asked me... She had the effrontery
要我幫助博弗特
to ask me to back Julius.
她要我別見死不救
Not to desert him, she said.
幫他們湯森德家族度過難關
To stand behind our common lineage in the Townsend family.
幫助博弗特  就等於幫助他們全家族
If you back Julius, you can see the family through.
如果你見死不救
If you don't,
我們就都會
we will all,
永遠抬不起頭來
every one of us, fall into dishonour.
我告訴她
I said to her...
咱們明戈特家
Honour's always been honour.
做事一向光明磊落
And honesty's always been honesty in Manson Mingott's house.
只要我一息尚存  絕不做違背良心之事
And will be, till I'm carried out feet-first.
她回答說  如果你敢相信她所說的  但我的名譽怎麼辦  姑姑
And then she said, if you can believe this, "But my name, Auntie."
我的名譽怎麼辦
But my name, Auntie.
我叫瑞吉娜·湯森德
My name's Regina Townsend.
於是我對她說
And I said to her...
你在博弗特娶你入門時  就已冠上夫姓
Your name was Beaufort when he covered you with jewels,
既使現今他已使你蒙羞  你仍姓博弗特
and it's got to stay Beaufort, now that he's covered you with shame.
然後我就崩潰了
And then I gave out,
就這麼崩潰了
simply gave out.
現在大伙全等著參加我的葬禮
And now family is arriving from all over,
然後他們又需要有人招待
expecting a funeral, and they'll have to be entertained.
真不知大夫通知了多少人
I don't know how many notes Bencomb sent out.
- 希望我們能幫得上忙  - 艾倫就快來了
- If there's anything we can do to help out... - Well, my Ellen is coming.
我指名要她來
I expressly asked for her.
她的火車今天到  如果你肯去接她的話
She arrives this afternoon on the train. If you could fetch her...
當然  如果梅要用四輪馬車的話  我去乘輪渡
Of course. If May will send the brougham, I'll take the ferry.
好  謝謝
Fine. Fine. Thank you.
瞧  這不就成了
There? You see, Granny? Everyone will be settled.
謝謝你  乖孫  願上天保佑你
Thank you, dear. Bless you.
我不想讓奶奶操心
I didn't want to worry Granny,
可是你今天要去華盛頓
but how can you meet Ellen and bring her back here
怎麼去接艾倫呢
if you have to go to Washington yourself this afternoon?
我不去了  早上萊特布賴爾告訴我
I'm not going. The case is off, postponed.
開庭延期了
I heard from Letterblair this morning.
延期  這怎麼可能
Postponed? How odd.
早上我媽也收到他的通知
Mama had a note from him this morning as well.
他也很關心奶奶  但無法前來
He was concerned about Granny, but had to be away.
他正在最高法院打一場專利官司
He was arguing a big patent case before the Supreme Court.
一場專利的官司
You did say it was a patent case, didn't you?
大家都無法出庭
Well, that's it. The whole office can't go.
萊特布賴爾只好自己去了
Letterblair decided to go himself.
這不叫延期
So then, it's not postponed?
對  可是我出庭的日期是延了
No, but my going is.
他計算過搭車和乘船
He knew it was two hours by ferry
從紐澤西市賓州車站到明戈特奶奶家
and carriage from the Pennsylvania terminus in Jersey City back to Mrs. Mingott's.
需要兩小時
All of two hours.
或許多一點
And maybe a little more.
- 沒想到我會來吧  - 對
- You didn't expect me today. - No.
我差點去華盛頓找你  我們差點見不到面
I nearly came to Washington to see you. We would have missed each other.
明戈特奶奶要我來接你  她好多了
It was Granny Mingott who sent me. She's much better.
我幾乎把你給忘了
You know, I hardly remembered you.
幾乎把我給忘了
Hardly remembered?
每次都是如此
I mean... I mean, each time is the same.
每回你都給帶我全新的感受
You happen to me all over again.
我知道
Yes, I know.
我也有相同的感受
For me, too.
我們不能再這樣耗下去了
Ellen, we can't stay like this. It can't last.
我們必須面對現實
I think we should look at reality, not dreams.
我要跟你長相廝守
I just want us to be together.
我不可能嫁給你的
I can't be your wife, Newland.
難道要我當你情婦嗎
Is it your idea I should live with you as your mistress?
我想
I want...
我想要帶你遠走高飛
Somehow I want to get away with you,
到一個沒有妻妾之分的地方
and find a world where words like that don't exist.
噢  親愛的
Oh, my dear.
什麼地方  你去過嗎
Where is that country? Have you ever been there?
到哪兒可以逃過良心的譴責呢
Is there anywhere we can be happy behind the backs of people who trust us?
我不在乎
I'm beyond caring about that.
你不是這種人
No, you're not.
你從未離經叛道過
You've never been beyond that.
而我卻是過來人
I have.
我瞭解那種感受  我們是不可能結合的
I know what it looks like. It's no place for us.
為何停車  奶奶不住這裏
Why are... Why are we stopping? This isn't Granny's.
我要在這兒下車
No. I'll get out here.
你說得對  我不該來的
You were right. I shouldn't have come today.
你在看什麼
What are you reading?
一本有關日本的書
It's a book about Japan.
為何讀它
Why?
我也不知道
I don't know.
因為那是不同的國家
Because it's a different country.
你不是愛讀詩嗎
You used to read poetry.
我喜歡你念詩給我聽
It was so nice when you read it to me.
紐倫德
Newland.
你會感冒的
You'll catch your death.
當然
Of course.
他發現他已有如行屍走肉
But then he realised, "I am dead.
死了好幾個月
"I've been dead for months and months."
他突然想到她可以死掉
Then it occurred to him that she might die.
世事難料  健康的年輕人也可能遭遇不測
People did. Young people, healthy people did.
也許她會死  讓他恢復自由
She might die and set him free.
紐倫德
Newland?
艾倫  我非見你不可
Ellen, I have to see you.
你何時離開
I didn't know when you were leaving again.
我不走了
I'm... I'm not leaving.
奶奶要我留下來照顧她
Granny's asked me to stay and take care of her.
那麼我們得好好談談
Then we have to talk now.
我得到瑞吉娜家去  坐奶奶的車去
I'm due at Regina Beaufort's. Granny lent me her carriage.
奶奶說博弗特是個無賴  我先生也一樣
I know Granny says Julius Beaufort is a scoundrel,
而全家族的人卻都要我回到他身旁
but so is my husband, and the family still want me to go back to him.
只有奶奶是個明理之人  她甚至時常接濟我
Only Granny understands. She's even seen to my allowance.
我必須找個地方和你獨處
I have to see you, somewhere we can be alone.
- 在紐約嗎  - 只要是能獨處的地方
- In New York? - Alone. Somewhere we can be alone.
明天下午兩點半美術館見
The art museum in the park, 2:30 tomorrow.
我在門口等你
I'll be at the door.
用途不詳
你到紐約來只因你怕
You came to New York because you were afraid.
- 怕什麼  - 怕我去華盛頓找你
- Afraid? - Of my coming to Washington.
我以為在紐約會比較安全
I thought I would be safer.
怕我打擾你
Safer from me?
艾倫
Ellen?
怕
S...
怕自己陷得太深嗎
Safer from loving me?
可以給你一次然後回家去嗎
Shall I come to you once and then go home?
給我一次吧
Come to me once then.
什麼時候
When?
明天
Tomorrow.
後天吧
The day after.
奧蘭斯卡夫人  第五大道  八零九號
抱歉  我回來晚了  沒讓你操心吧
I'm sorry I'm late. You weren't worried, were you?
現在很晚嗎
Is it late?
已經七點多了
It's past 7:00.
我和艾倫在奶奶家聊
I stayed at Granny's because Cousin Ellen came in.
她非常友好  我們聊得很開心  就像是從前的她
We had a wonderful talk. She was so dear, just like the old Ellen.
奶奶好喜歡她
Granny was so charmed by her.
不過她有時真讓人反感
But you can see, though, how the family's been annoyed with her at times.
例如坐奶奶的車去看博弗特太太
Going to see Regina Beaufort in Granny's carriage and...
今晚要出去吃嗎
Are we dining out tonight?
你今天還沒親我
You haven't kissed me today.
當時紐約人的習慣
It was the custom in old New York
新婚的前幾年
for brides to appear in their wedding dress
新嫁娘都穿著結婚禮服出門
during the first year or two of marriage.
但梅從歐洲回來後
But May, since returning from Europe,
今晚是她第一次穿上結婚禮服
had not worn her bridal satin until this evening.
抱歉  梅  我的頭好痛
May, I'm sorry. My head's bursting.
別告訴任何人  我們回家吧
Please don't tell anyone. Come home with me now.
你不是該休息
Shouldn't you rest?
我的頭好多了
My head's not as bad as that.
有件事我得告訴你
And there's something important I have to say to you right away.
我得和你談談
May, there is something that I've got to tell you.
關於我自己
About myself.
奧蘭斯卡夫人
Madame Olenska...
為何要在今晚談她
Why should we talk about Ellen tonight?
因為我早就該說了
Because I should have spoken before and...
真有那麼重要嗎
Is it really worthwhile, dear?
我知道有時我對她過於冷淡
I know I've been unfair to her at times.
或許你也一樣
Perhaps we all have.
你是最瞭解她的人
You've understood her better than any of us, I suppose,
但現已經事過境遷了
but does it really matter now that it's all over?
事過境遷  什麼意思
How do you mean, "over"?
她馬上就要回歐洲了
Why, since she's going back to Europe so soon.
儘管奶奶很失望  但她能體諒
Granny's approved, and understands.
她願意給她一筆錢
She's disappointed, of course,
讓她不用再仰賴伯爵
but she's arranged to make Ellen financially independent of the Count.
我以為你今天在辦公室聽說了
I... I thought you would have heard today at your offices.
- 不可能  - 不可能
- It's impossible. - Impossible?
她本可以住在紐約
Certainly she could have stayed here with Granny's extra money,
只是她不要
but I guess she's given us up, after all.
你怎麼會知道
How do you know that?
艾倫親口說的  我說過我昨天在奶奶家遇見她
From Ellen. I told you, I saw her at Granny's yesterday.
她昨天告訴你的
And she told you that, yesterday?
不是  今天下午我收到她的來信
No. She sent me a note this afternoon.
想看嗎
Do you want to see it?
我以為你已經知道了
I thought you knew.
親愛的梅  我終於讓奶奶瞭解
"May, dear, I have at last made Granny understand
我這次來  只是想看看她
"that my visit to her could be no more than a visit,
這一回她和以前一樣疼我
"and she has been as kind and generous as ever."
"And she has been as kind and generous as ever.
她知道我回歐洲後  必須自食其力
"She sees now that if I return to Europe, I must live by myself.
我急於回華盛頓打包  下周就搭船回歐洲
"I am hurrying back to Washington to pack up, and I sail next week.
我不在時要好好照顧她
"You be must very good to Granny when I'm gone,
就像你待我那樣
"as good as you've always been to me.
萬一有人想說服我留下來
"If any of my friends wish to urge me to change my mind,
請他們別白費唇舌
"please tell them it would be utterly useless."
"... tell them it would be utterly useless."
她為何寫這封信給你
Why did she write this?
大概是我們昨天聊了很多吧
I suppose because we talked things over yesterday.
聊什麼
What things?
我說我怕自己待她不夠好
I told her that I was afraid I hadn't always been fair to her,
因為我不瞭解她所受的苦
that I hadn't always understood how hard it must have been for her here.
我知道她很信任你
I knew you'd be the one friend she could always count on,
我要她知道  我跟你一樣支持她
and I wanted her to know that you and I were the same in all of our feelings.
她瞭解我為何說這一番話
She understood why I wanted to tell her this.
她是個善解人意的人
I think she understands everything.
我的頭也好痛
My head aches too.
- 晚安  親愛的  - 晚安
- Good night, dear. - Good night.
誠如阿切爾的母親所說
It was, as Mrs. Archer said to Mrs. Welland,
新婚夫婦首次請客是件大事
a great event for a young couple to give their first dinner,
必須做到盡善盡美
and it was not to be undertaken lightly.
要請個大廚
There was a hired chef,
兩個上菜的  用最上等的玫瑰
two borrowed footmen, roses from Henderson's,
檸檬汁甜酒  鑲金邊的菜單
Roman punch and menus on gilt-edged cards.
馮·德·萊登夫婦不僅出席了
It was considered a particular triumph that the van der Luydens,
還因梅之邀  留在紐約
at May's request, stayed in the city to be present
參加奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人的送別會
at her farewell dinner for the Countess Olenska.
受辱後你必須離開紐約
You have to leave New York after the disgrace...
阿切爾將一桌慈面善目的人
Archer saw all the harmless-looking people
視為一群沉默的共謀者
at the table as a band of quiet conspirators,
破壞著他和艾倫的好事
with himself and Ellen the centre of their conspiracy.
他猜想著這幾個月來
He guessed himself to have been for months the centre
大家都默默盯著
of countless silently observing eyes
豎起耳朵靜靜地聽
and patiently listening ears.
他體會到他們成功地
He understood that somehow the separation
把他和他情人分開了
between himself and the partner of his guilt had been achieved.
他也瞭解到大夥兒都站在梅那一邊
And he knew that now the whole tribe had rallied around his wife.
他成了眾矢之的
He was a prisoner in the centre of an armed camp.
我在想他們是否會回來
I wonder if they'll ever get it back.
博弗特太太病了
Regina's not well at all,
但博弗特仍然
but that doesn't stop Beaufort from devoting as much time
常和安妮·瑞茵廝混
to Annie Ring as he can manage.
老實說
The best thing Beaufort could do
博弗特應該去北卡找她
would be to go and stay at Regina's little place in North Carolina.
他可以在那兒養馬
He could breed trotters...
他寄給艾倫的鑰匙
And the key to his release
當天即被返還
had been returned the day before.
被原封不動寄了回來
By mail. Unopened.
博弗特根本不擔心婚外情曝光
He may stay here as a deliberate challenge to the outrage he's created.
說不定他還會競選總統呢
Perhaps he'll run for public office.
安妮·瑞茵會成為他的第一夫人嗎
Then will Annie Ring be his first lady?
從華盛頓回來累嗎
Was your trip from Washington very tiring?
火車上悶得要命
The heat on the train was dreadful.
出遠門總是辛苦的
But all travel has its hardships.
能換個環境就值得了
Well, whatever they may be, they're worth it just to get away.
我也打算出遠門
I mean to do a lot of travelling myself soon.
菲利普  一起去冒險吧
What about you, Philip? What about a little adventure?
雅典或是伊斯麥  或是君士坦丁堡
Athens and Smyrna, maybe even Constantinople.
或許吧  或許吧
Possibly. Possibly.
千萬別去拿坡裏
But not Naples.
大夫說那兒有流行病
Dr Bencomb says there's a fever.
噢  真的嗎  拿坡裏有流行病
Oh, really? A fever in Naples.
那麼我就去印度吧
Well, there's always India, of course.
在印度至少得待三周才夠
You must have three weeks to do India properly.
沒錯
Absolutely.
博弗特雖然未受邀
Beaufort may not receive invitations any more,
但仍然保持高姿態
but it's clear he still maintains a certain position.
聽說是平躺在床上的姿態
Horizontal from all I've heard.
如果他再胡搞下去
If things go on like this, we'll be seeing our children
恐怕我們的後代會跟他的私生子結婚
fighting for invitations to swindlers' houses and marrying Beaufort's bastards.
他在外面生了幾個
Has he got any?
各位  留點口德
Be careful there, gentlemen. Draw it mild. Draw it mild.
社會對蕩婦總能容忍
Society has a history of tolerating vulgar women after all.
在某種程度上
Up to a point.
容忍那種人的唯一原因
But once it tolerates a man of that kind,
- 只能是為了繼承權  - 你是否注意到了
- the only prospect is total disinheritance... - Have you ever noticed
廚子最差的人家
it's the people with the worst cooks who are always yelling
總是嫌別人家的菜難吃
about being poisoned when they dine out?
我以為萊弗茨是精於此項
Lefferts used to be a little more adept, I thought.
但只要懂得步法
But then grace is not always required
這一門是不需美態的
as long as one knows the steps.
真不知萊弗茨這傢伙
I've never heard Lefferts so abound in the sentiments
幾時成了衛道人士
that adorn Christian manhood.
憤怒和恐懼所爆發出的威力一樣傷人
Indignation lends a scathing eloquence.
家裏的壓力無窮無盡
It's almost as effective as fear. The pressure at home must be unrelenting.
我從未聽過如此讚美家庭的話
I never expected to hear such a paean to the sanctity...
我母親想把她那尊維納斯銅像送給我們
My mother had a bronze reduction of the Venus De Milo she wanted to give us...
他們不動聲色地
The silent organisation
團結起來  決定痛懲不守規範的人
which held this whole small world together was determined to put itself on record.
從未有人質疑  奧蘭斯卡夫人的行為有違禮教
It had never for a moment questioned the propriety of Madame Olenska's conduct.
也從未有人質疑紐倫德的忠誠
It had never questioned Archer's fidelity.
從未有人聽說  懷疑  或甚至相信
And it had never heard of, suspected or even conceived possible
他們有任何不軌
anything at all to the contrary.
艾倫
Ellen.
從這一頓完美演出的飯局
From the seamless performance of this ritual,
阿切爾知道  紐約全城都認定他和奧蘭斯卡夫人是情人
Archer knew that New York believed him to be Madame Olenska's lover.
我們在聊舞會的事
We were discussing the Martha Washington ball.
我們想在復活節當周辦個愛盲舞會
Yes, we have it during Easter week to benefit the blind society.
他們做的工作棒極了
They do excellent work.
勞倫斯
Lawrence. Lawrence...
他第一次瞭解到
And he understood for the first time
自己的太太也這麼認為
that his wife shared the belief.
你一定要來歐洲看我
You must come visit me when you do.
等一切安頓好  我會寫信回來的
I'll write you as soon as I'm settled and let you know where I am.
那太好了
Yes, that would be lovely.
我送你上馬車
Shall I see you to your carriage?
我們正要送她回家
We are driving dear Ellen home.
再見
Good-bye.
再見  巴黎見了
Good-bye. And I'll see you very soon in Paris.
噢  希望你和梅能來
Oh, if you and May could come.
可以走了嗎
Shall we make our way to the carriage, my dear?
今晚真開心
Delightful evening, Newland.
晚安  紐倫德
Good night, Newland.
晚安  西勒頓  拉瑞
Good night, Sillerton. Good night, Larry.
今夜的晚宴很棒吧
It did go off beautifully, didn't it?
噢  對
Oh, yes.
我能進來聊聊嗎
May I come in and talk it over?
當然  可是你一定很想睡了
Of course. But you must be very sleepy.
- 不  我想和你聊聊  - 好
- No, I'm not. I'd like to be with you a little. - Fine.
如果你願意
If you feel up to it, May,
我想告訴你一件事
there is something that I've been wanting to talk to you about.
那一夜就想告訴你的那件事
And I tried to talk to you the other evening.
是的  有關你自己的事
Yes, dear. Something about yourself.
對  有關我自己的事
About myself, yes.
真不知該從何說起
It's so difficult to find the right words.
我覺得好累
But it's just that I feel so terribly tired at the moment.
我想
And I think...
而且每況愈下
Each day a little more so.
我想如果我休息一陣子  或許對大家都有好處
And I think it would be better for everyone if I were to make a break.
你是指辭職
You mean give up the law?
辭職當然也是一部分
Well, certainly that would be a part of it. And also just to...
然後出國
Just to get away.
我想出去旅行
I... I'd like to do some travelling.
歐洲
To Europe or...
或是更遠的地方
Perhaps even farther.
多遠
How far?
我也不知道
I don't know. I thought...
印度或是日本吧
India or Japan.
像那麼遠的地方
As far as that?
這個嘛
Well...
恐怕你不能去  親愛的
I'm afraid you can't, dear.
除非你帶我去
Not unless you take me with you.
只怕醫生不會同意
That is, if the doctors will let me go, and I'm afraid they won't.
紐倫德  早上才確定的
Newland, I've been sure of something since this morning,
我一直想找機會告訴你
and I've been longing to tell you.
噢  親愛的
Oh, my dear.
意外吧
You didn't guess?
對  我希望  但
No. I mean, of course, I... I hoped, but...
你還告訴了誰
Have you told anyone else?
只有我媽媽和你母親
Only Mamma and your mother...
還有艾倫
And Ellen.
我說過我們聊了很久  而且她人很好
I told you we had a long talk one afternoon and how wonderful she was to me.
你不想讓她知道嗎
Did you mind my telling her, Newland?
怎麼會呢
Mind? Why should I?
那已經是兩星期前的事了吧
But that was two weeks ago, wasn't it?
你不是今天才確定的嗎
I thought you just said you weren't sure till today?
當時我是不確定
No, I... I wasn't sure then,
但我還是告訴她了
but I told her I was.
而且呢  我猜對了
And you see, I was right.
就在這書房
It was the room
他生命中最真實的事發生了
in which most of the real things of his life had happened.
他們的長子西奧多
Their eldest boy, Theodore,
無法在隆冬抱出門
too delicate to be taken to church in midwinter,
因此就在這兒受洗
had been christened there.
我以聖父
I baptise thee in the name of the Father,
聖子
and of the son,
以及聖靈的名義  為你施洗禮
and of the holy spirit.
泰德就在這裏學走路
It was here that Ted took his first steps.
紐倫德夫婦也常在此
And it was here that Archer and his wife always discussed
討論子女的未來
the future of all their children.
比爾對考古有興趣
Bill's interest in archaeology,
瑪麗喜歡體育和慈善活動
Mary's passion for sports and philanthropy,
熱愛藝術的泰德想當建築師
Ted's inclination toward art that led to a job with an architect,
和從事室內裝潢的工作
as well as some considerable redecoration.
瑪麗在這裏宣佈喜訊
It was in this room that Mary had announced her engagement...
我真為你開心
I'm so happy for you.
她嫁給了拉瑞·萊弗茨的兒子
To the dullest and most reliable of Larry Lefferts' many sons.
紐倫德也在這裏親吻了她
And it was in this room, too, that her father had kissed her
然後坐車陪她上教堂結婚
through her wedding veil before they motored to Grace Church.
紐倫德是個賢夫慈父
He was a dutiful and loving father, and a faithful husband.
當梅因照顧比爾而感染肺炎過世
When May died of infectious pneumonia after nursing Bill safely through,
他深深哀悼
he had honestly mourned her.
世界在她的歲月中粉碎瓦解
The world of her youth had fallen into pieces
然後形成一個新世界  而她並未察覺
and rebuilt itself without her ever noticing.
純真無邪的她
This hard, bright blindness,
似乎很難意識到週遭的變動
her incapacity to recognise change,
因此兒女就像阿切爾一樣  不願對她透露內心的看法
made her children conceal their views from her, just as Archer concealed his.
她死時仍然覺得這世界是一片樂土
She died thinking the world a good place,
充滿愛與和諧  就像她的家庭一樣
full of loving and harmonious households like her own.
紐倫德·阿切爾在五十七歲時
Newland Archer, in his 57th year,
追憶過去  感慨萬千
mourned his past and honoured it.
喂
Yes, hello? Hello?
芝哥加電話
Chicago wants you.
喂
Hello?
- 爸  - 泰德  是你嗎
- Dad? - Is that you, Ted?
爸  我剛完工
Dad, I'm just about finished out here,
但客戶要求我去看幾座花園  再著手設計
but my client wants me to look at some gardens before I start designing.
不錯嘛  在哪兒
That sounds fine. Where?
- 歐洲  - 天啊
- Europe. - Gracious.
我下週三搭船過去
I'll have to sail next Wednesday on the Mauretania.
什麼  要錯過自己的婚禮嗎
What, and miss the wedding?
我想安妮會等我的
I think Annie will wait for me.
我一號就回來了  趕得上五號的婚禮
I'll be back on the 1st, and our wedding's not till the 5th.
沒想到你還記得日期
I'm surprised you remember the date.
- 希望你能和我一起去  - 什麼
- Well... Dad, I was hoping you'd join me. - What?
我需要你提醒我孰重孰輕
I'll need you to remind me of what's important.
結婚前的最後一次父子同游
What do you say? It will be our last father-and-son trip.
- 感謝你的邀請  - 太好了
- Well, Ted, I do appreciate the invitation... - Wonderful!
明天記得訂船票
Can you call the Cunard office first thing tomorrow?
但我得取消
But it would take me till next Wednesday just to cancel my...
我不想聽  大西洋正在召喚我們
I won't hear it, Dad. The Atlantic is calling us.
週一我就到紐約
I'll be in New York on Monday, and I'll contact you then.
- 什麼時候  - 星期一
- You'll be in New... - On Monday.
我盡力就是了
I'll see what I can do.
訂購船票  爸
Settle the tickets, Dad.
我不能拍胸脯保證  我盡力就是了
I can't promise anything, Ted. I'll see what I can do. All right.
- 再見  - 再見
- Bye-bye. - Bye.
我要和透娜去凡爾賽宮  你去不去
I'm going out to Versailles with Tourneur. Will you join us?
我想去羅浮宮
I thought I'd go to the Louvre.
那麼我去找你
I'll meet you there later then.
我跟奧蘭斯卡伯爵夫人約在五點半見
Countess Olenska's expecting us at 5:30.
什麼
What?
我沒告訴你嗎
Didn't I tell you?
安妮要我在巴黎為她做三件事
Annie made me swear to do three things in Paris.
幫她買套德彪西的最新曲譜合輯
Get her the score of the last Debussy songs,
去大木偶劇院  以及去看奧蘭斯卡夫人
go to the Grand Guignol, and see Madame Olenska.
博弗特送安妮來索邦大學讀書時
You know, she was awfully good to Annie
她待她好極了
when Mr. Beaufort sent her over to the Sorbonne.
伯爵夫人跟博弗特的前妻關係不太好  對嗎
Wasn't the Countess friendly with Mr. Beaufort's first wife or something?
博弗特先生是這麼說的
I think Mrs. Beaufort said that she was.
總之  早上我打了電話給伯爵夫人
In any case, I called the Countess first thing this morning,
告訴她我是她的外甥
introduced myself as her cousin.
你提到過我也來了嗎
Did you tell her I was here, Ted?
當然  有何不可
Of course. Why not?
她聽起來很可愛  她一向如此嗎
She sounds lovely. Was she?
可愛
Lovely?
我不知道  她變了
I don't know. She was different.
每當憶起艾倫·奧蘭斯卡
Whenever he thought of Ellen Olenska,
他總感覺虛幻寧靜
it had been abstractly, serenely,
宛如畫中的仕女
like an imaginary loved one in a book or picture.
她象徵他所錯失的一切
She had become the complete vision of all that he had missed.
我才五十七歲啊
I'm only 57.
博弗特再婚時
Did Mr. Beaufort really have such a bad time of it
阻力真有這麼大嗎
when he wanted to remarry?
大家都不謙讓他一分
No one wanted to give him an inch?
或許是以前謙讓過太多
Perhaps because he'd already taken so much.
但現在誰還記得  誰還在乎呢
As if anyone remembers any more, or cares.
安妮·瑞茵為他生了個寶貝女兒  你真幸運
Well, Annie Ring and he did have a lovely daughter. You're very lucky.
你是指我們都很幸運
We're very lucky, you mean.
當然
Yes, of course that's what I mean.
人生至此  早已事過境遷
So considering how that all turned out, and all the time that's gone by,
你怎麼還要抗拒呢
I don't see how you can resist.
你們結婚  我一開始也無法接受
I did have some resistance at first to your marriage, as I told you...
我是指你拒絕見一個你差點為她犧牲一切的女人
No. I mean resist seeing the woman you almost threw everything over for.
只是你懸崖勒馬了
Only you didn't.
我懸崖勒馬
I didn't?
沒錯
No.
但母親說
But Mother said that she knew
- 我們都會安然無恙的  - 你母親
- we would be safe with you. - Your mother?
還記得她臨終的前一天  要單獨跟我談嗎
Yes. The day before she died she asked to see me alone. Remember?
她說她放心把這個家交給你
She said she knew we were safe with you,
一直如此安心
and always would be,
因為你曾答應她
because once, when she asked you to,
放棄你的最愛
you gave up the thing that you wanted most.
她從未提起此事
She never asked.
她從未要求過我
She never asked me.
一會兒之後  他對泰德的直率不再感到懊惱
After a little while he did not regret Ted's indiscretion.
他的心結終於鬆綁
It seemed to take an iron band from his heart to know that,
畢竟  終究有人猜到而且憐憫過他
after all, someone had guessed and pitied,
而那個人居然是自己的太太  這更叫他感動莫名
and that it should have been his wife moved him inexpressibly.
門童說她住在三樓
The porter says it's the third floor.
一定是有兩篷的那一戶
Must be the one with the awnings.
快六點了
It's nearly 6:00.
我想坐一會兒
I think I'll just sit for a while.
你不想上去嗎
Do you mean you won't come?
- 真的不上去嗎  - 我也不知道
- You really won't come at all? - I don't know.
她不會理解的
She won't understand.
去吧  泰德  也許我隨後就到
Go on, Ted. Maybe I'll follow you.
我該怎麼告訴她
What will I tell her?
你不是最能言善道了嗎
Don't you always have something to say?
我說你很老派
I'll tell her you're old-fashioned,
堅持走樓梯  而不願意去乘電梯
and you insist on walking up three flights instead of taking the elevator.
就說我很老派
Just say I'm old-fashioned.
這足夠了  去吧
That should be enough. Go on.
去吧
Go on.
獻 給 我 的 父 親    路 希 安 諾 · 查 爾 斯 · 斯 科 塞 斯
================================
( 導 演 的 父 親 在 影 片 即 將 上 映 前 離 世 )
旁 白 : 喬 安 娜 · 伍 德 沃 德